<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief memorial wherein the present case of the antient leasees, the inward pawn sub-tenants, and the outward pawn present tenants, of the Royal exchange [is] ... stated. : As also some animadversions ... relating to the ... revenue of the said place ... / By an unfeigned welwisher to the flourishing estate of the city of London ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77440</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170805</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504354</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504354</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171654</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77440)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171654)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2584:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief memorial wherein the present case of the antient leasees, the inward pawn sub-tenants, and the outward pawn present tenants, of the Royal exchange [is] ... stated. : As also some animadversions ... relating to the ... revenue of the said place ... / By an unfeigned welwisher to the flourishing estate of the city of London ...</title>
                  <author>T. P. (Theophilus Philalethes)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], [49] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed Anno Dom. 1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed in Greek: Theophilus Philalethes.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Royal Exchange (London, England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Building leases --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171654:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Brief MEMORIAL WHEREIN The preſent Caſe of the Antient Leaſees, the Inward Pawn Sub-Tenants, and the Outward Pawn preſent Tenants, of the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> truely, and impartially STATED. AS ALSO Some ANIMADVERSIONS and remarkable paſſages relating to the preſent and publique revenue of the ſaid Place: with ſome modeſt propoſals for the future benefit and moſt certain advantage of the ſame. HUMBLY Preſented To the Conſideration of the Right Honourable Sir <hi>Robert Viner</hi> Knight and Baronet, Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London:</hi> and to the reſt of the Right Worſhipful and Worthy Members of the grand Committee for <hi>GRESHAM</hi> Affairs.</p>
            <p>By an Unfeigned Welwiſher to the Flouriſhing Eſtate of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and in particular to all the preſent Inhabitants of the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> within the ſaid Place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed Anno Dom. 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171654:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I fairly ſalute thee, if Courteous if not whoever thou art that takeſt up this ſmall peice into thy hands, and peradventure at firſt ſight art ſomewhat concerned and offended at the very title-page thereof. I would adviſe thee by all means to forbear railing againſt it, (rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and invectives being no powerful charms, but rather weak and contemptible means to convince the reaſons of men) until thou haſt diligently and throughly (laying aſide all prejudice) peruſed and examined the ſame And that, not then neither (unleſs thou haſt a mind to betray at once too much of thy humane frailty and imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillity) without thou art able to appear upon the ſtage and expoſe to publick view more ſolid and ſubſtantial arguments, than are herein contained, in confutation thereof. This I thought requiſite to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe thee, by reaſon I do already foreſee an approaching ſtorm upon this very accompt. But yet if thou haſt a mind, and art wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to enter the liſts; I will aſſure thee for thy incouragement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, thou ſhalt find ſo Fair, ſo Noble, ſo generous a Combatant, that if thy arguments are concluſive, he ſhall be as willing and ready to make an ingenuous and publick recantation of his preſent mistakes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171654:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable, and to the Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful Committee for <hi>Greſham</hi> Affairs.</head>
            <head type="sub">My Lord Maior and you the worthy Knights and Gentlemen, Members of the grand Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee.</head>
            <p>HAving for ſeveral years laſt paſt, been very converſant and held a good correſpondence with the inhabitants, (many of them being my worthy and much reſpected friends and intimate acquaintance) of your Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change. I am able to ſay this of them by experience, that I do verily believe, there is no particular number of people whatſoever (take them number for number,) within the walls of your City of <hi>London</hi> and Suburbs thereof (more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conſidering there being ſo many of the ſame trade) as do live more peaceably and lovingly together than theſe do. A notable inſtance hereof (as a confirmation of what I have here aſſerted) may plainly appear, by their loving and neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171654:3"/>meeting together every 17th. day of <hi>November</hi> yearly, to celebrate and ſollemnize the ever bleſſed memory of <hi>Queen Elizabeth's</hi> Coronation, whom (as our Anceſtours have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto us) gave the firſt name and appellation unto your Royal Exchange, At which time alſo, they have their Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin <hi>pro tempore,</hi> that ſo they may be excited, and ſtirred up to works of Charity unto their decayed Members, and for the more Grace, Gravity and Sobriety of their preſent ſollemnity: And the front of their Stewards printed Tickets for their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual invitation, doth uſually run after this manner, <hi>Viz. For the Continuance of Amity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and our ancient Society, you are hereby deſired,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But ſo it is <hi>(May it pleaſe your good Lordſhip and Worſhips)</hi> that ſometime before, and ſince the late dreadful fire, there have been (upon ſeveral pretences) ſuch animoſities, feuds and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions riſen amongſt them, very few comparatively (the more is the Pity) being of that moſt heroick, and noble Spirit, and temper; as to mind the publick good and concernment of the ſaid place before their own private and particular ſelf intereſt) ſo that by means thereof, it hath doubtleſs very much hindred and obſtructed the preſent flouriſhing eſtate of your Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, as by the ſequel of this memorial (the which by the inſtance and requeſt of ſome particular Friends is now expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to publick view) will more fully and plainly appear.</p>
            <p>The Premiſes conſidered, and as a member of the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> having a very great kindneſs, vallue and reſpect for your Royal Exchange, and in particular for ſeveral of my good Friends and Acquaintance within the ſaid Place, I was much affected therewith, and thereupon, of late, have made it my buſineſs ſomewhat to enquire into the true ſtate of Affairs, (and truly before my ſtrict enquiry by reaſon of the perpetual clamors, and fair pretences of every Party, I found it was a very hard matter rightly to underſtand them) as to their ſaid Animoſities before
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171654:3"/>mentioned. And herein it was many times a pleaſant diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement to hear theſe conteſting parties, ſo much at variance and contention one with another, when I obſerved that intereſt, particular ſelf intereſt with moſt of them, (eſpecially among the grandees) lay ſtill at the bottom. Yet not ſuffering my ſelf to be biaſſed, (although I did many times love to take the weakeſt part, being my natural conſtitution to vindicate the oppreſſed innocent) nor to be born down with the clamours and railings, but with the reaſons of Men. I got this fair ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage thereby as (I am perſwaded) in ſome good meaſure to inform both my ſelf, and you, of the right of the caſe: And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole matter, I do find, that their ſaid animoſities are never likely to be reconciled (and ſo conſequently your Royal Exchange never likely to be in a flouriſhing condition) untill you who are the worthy Members of the grand Committee, ſhall put your helping hands to the Plough, &amp; ſhall pleaſe by the interpoſition of your power and authority to accompliſh the ſame. Wherefore that ſo happy and ſo deſirable an effect (for as the Schoolmen ſay, <hi>ſublata cauſa tollitur effectus</hi>) as the flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition of your Royal Exchange, may in your dayes (that is during your Seſſions as members of this Honourable Court) be compleately and effectually accompliſhed: The Authour thought, it would be an acceptable ſervice to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of thoſe who are concerned upon your Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, (the antient Leaſees only excepted) to preſent you with a memorial (wherein all your Tenants caſes ſhould be fairly and truly ſtated) the which in all the ſubmiſſive and reſpective terms imaginable, he doth here moſt humbly preſent unto your Lordſhip and Worſhips moſt grave and prudent conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>This being premiſed by way of introduction, I am now to give a particular account of all theſe conteſting Parties before mentioned, and herein I ſhall not (neither for Fear nor Favour) mince the matter before you, whereby to conceal any thing as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171654:4"/>material to my preſent purpoſe or requiſite and neceſſary for your information, ſo that all things appearing ſo fair, naked and open (and driving on no deſign of particular ſelf intereſt, enough to marr the beſt cauſe in the world) I hope in time there will be ſuch a right underſtanding between you and your preſent Tenants, as that neither you nor they for the future will have any cauſe to repent the publication hereof.</p>
            <p>And now theſe conteſting Parties, in and related unto the Royal Exchange, you have them reduced already in the Title page unto theſe three heads, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Antient Leaſees.</item>
               <item>2. The inward Pawn Sub-tenants.</item>
               <item>3. The outward pawn Preſent-Tenants.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And all theſe I will take them in their Order as here they preſent themſelves, in manner and form as followeth.</p>
            <p>And firſt for the Antient Leaſees (they being Stars of the firſt magnitude I muſt give them the precedency) I preſume it is not neceſſary nor requiſite, that I ſhould give you a particular Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue here in print of every one of them by name, (this were indeed to pull down an old houſe here, upon my Head) but only let you know, that as ſuch, they are thoſe who before the late dreadful Fire had given over their Trades (having renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before hand ſeveral of them their Leaſees for 21 years) let their Shops (full of braded wares) at moſt unreaſonable rates, <hi>viz.</hi> for 30, 40, and 50 pounds <hi>per annum</hi> for one ſingle Shop in your Royal Exchange, and in fine they are ſuch, who for ſeveral years laſt paſt have lived, they and their Heires (and would willingly for ever be at the ſame lock, as making a better live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood thereby than keeping Shops themſelves) upon the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and careful endeavours of many poor young People, who by means thereof have not been able, comfortably to provide for themſelves and Families, nor to bear up under ſuch intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and inſupportable burthens.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:171654:4"/>
            <p>And of theſe Leaſees, there are two ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Antient.</item>
               <item>2. Modern.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I am forced to make uſe of, and borrow this diſtinction on purpoſe hereafter to avoid a miſtake, and a miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Leaſees themſelves. I call him a Modern Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, who is in actual poſſeſſion by Leaſe of his own Shop (and long may he peaecably and quietly enjoy his ſaid po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion,) and among theſe there are at this day here and there one, who have Leaſes of more Shops than their own; and theſe do alſo (like the precedent Leaſees) let the ſaid Shops at an extraordinary rate, and theſe men do now take up the cudgels and plead in the behalf of the Antient Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees (it being in this reſpect their own proper caſe) as if they were here alwaies perſonally preſent to defend themſelves. Wherefore theſe enſuing lines are not deſigned nor intended againſt them as they are Modern but as they are Antient Leaſees.</p>
            <p>And now to my preſent purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the men who after the late moſt dreadful Fire, did ſo bitterly exclaim againſt (like ſo many Bears robbed of their whelps: and yet clearly upon a miſtaken notion as the ſequel hereof will plainly demonſtrate) your building of double Pawns within your Royal Exchange, and that their Children as yet unborn would be bound to curſe thoſe who were the firſt projectors or petitioners for the ſame, although in the mean time (as if they had never heard of <hi>lex talionis</hi>) they do not ſay, whoſe Children will be bound to pray for them whoſe Fathers have been ruined and undone by wrack-rents, before they came to be Antient Leaſees. <hi>And More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,</hi> That a late Book, the Title whereof was <hi>LONDON'S NONS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CH,</hi> (wherein double Pawns by the Author there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was propoſed) deſerved to be burnt by the common Hangman for the contents thereof. Wherefore in vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all thoſe who did petition for double Pawns, and in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171654:5"/>particular for all thoſe who gave their ſuffrages for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of the ſaid Book. I dare here take up the cudgels and will fairly, and modeſtly argue the rationality, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſign of that Book, (as having diligently peruſed the ſame) againſt the ſtouteſt &amp; moſt rigid Leaſee of them all. And pray what was the deſign of that book, (if a man now may be ſo bold as to ask them) if any of you have read it, or have any deſire to peruſe the ſame, (I fear very few of the former Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees, by reaſon of the bitter railings and clamors of the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees againſt it, although licenſed by Authority, though it worth their peruſal) you will find that the main and principal deſign of the Author therein (and for the jocular and pleaſant part thereof he gives a particular account, in his Epiſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory to this Honourable Court) was, <hi>That inaſmuch as the grand Committee had voted for double Pawns, and that they had stretched the dimenſions of the ſaid Place, unto a far great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er compaſs than formerly, that they would pleaſe thereupon to make proviſion therein for four pair of ſtairs, and four Balco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies within the inward Walks thereof; and alſo that they would pleaſe to be moderate in their Rents and Fines, and that two ſides of the ſaid place might be converted into deep Shops and that the Trades therein, by the interpoſition of their authority (before they let any new Leaſes,) might be ſo orderly placed (juſt as it is at this day in the New Exchange, where two of the ſame Trade cannot be placed together) ſo as that they ſhould not interfere or be prejudicial one to another.</hi> Lo here now <hi>(in paucis Verbis)</hi> the deſign of that moſt malignant and contemptible Book, and if this was not then and will be ſtill the intereſt of your ſelves (in reſpect of your preſent, and future revenue) and alſo the intereſt of all your Tenants (as to their equal accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation) I muſt ingenuouſly here declare. I have no reaſon nor underſtanding (as to the premiſes) now left or remaining in me. But it is well that I have an inſtance ready at hand (which will be right worthy alſo of your Honours particular obſervation) for confirmation hereof, (and an inſtance taken
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171654:5"/>
               <hi>pro Confeſſo</hi> from an adverſe Party is a <hi>dilemma</hi> indeed) <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe very men, who did ſo much clamor, and moſt bitterly inveigh againſt the ſaid Book as ridiculous, nonſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical, ſcandalous (and many the like opprobrious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible terms) did in a ſhort time after come to the ſaid Authour, and to the reſt of your outward pawn Tenants, to requeſt them, that inaſmuch as they wanted Aire in their inward Walks, that they would pleaſe to joyn with them in an humble petition to the grand Committee, to procure themſelves four Balconies within the ſaid Place: unto the which they did very willingly and readily aſſent, although according to the narrow and ſtraight laced principles of meer policy and ſelf intereſt, it was a diſadvantage unto them, and although their petition was thereupon granted, yet the ſaid Balconies are now but a botch, in compariſon of what they might have been, had they been built before thoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Windows, (as a worthy member of this Committee, by name Sir <hi>Thomas Player</hi> coming upon a ſurveigh was pleaſed to call them) were firſt erected.</p>
            <p>And Moreover, that you may ſee how miſerably theſe men were miſtaken in their preſent notions, they would now be glad withal their hearts to ſee all thoſe things propoſed in the ſaid Book, really and effectually accompliſhed. For as dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pawns was therein propoſed, it would rather have forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied their wrack rents (the more would have been the pity) for the remaining time of their Leaſes, than have impaired or diminiſhed (which was their darling notion wherein they were ſo much in the dark) any part or parcel thereof. And therefore what ſhall a man ſay to theſe things, but only <hi>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum, horrendum, informe, ingens, cui lumen ademptum!</hi> and the truth of it is, undigeſted principles and falſe notions (as not being guided by reaſon) once ſucked in, hath been in all ages of moſt pernitious and dangerous conſequence both to Church and State. So that now as briefly as I could (and as the matter would bear) I have here given you the true ſtate
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171654:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>and preſent condition of theſe antient Leaſees, and as for their preſent deſign now on foot (and ſo furiouſly carried on withal the fair ſhows, and moſt ſpecious pretences imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) for Leaſes of 21 years (although their arguments for the ſame, as I could eaſily make appear, are but weak, ſophiſtical, fallacious and of a diſmal conſequence) the which looking with ſo ugly and deformed a countenance, I hope the Young men in the outward Walks will waſh their hands in innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and will not deſire to be of their Councels nor Faction therein, nor yet ſuffer themſelves to be admitted (though it ſeems ſome of them have been courted and invited thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, becauſe of going hand in hand to the grand Committee to make their deſign more feiſeable) but they have hitherto had the grace to refuſe themſelves to be Members of their private Cabal,</p>
            <p>And as for their Tenant-rights ſo much inſiſted upon and cryed up amongſt them, as much as was the great <hi>Diana</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Whereas <hi>in re vera</hi> after their Leaſes are expired they have no more legal right or pretence thereunto (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your propriety and eſtate) than a Porter that goes eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day along the Streets with his burthen at his back. And here I would willingly be informed by this Honourable Court, of this one queſtion, <hi>viz,</hi> Who hath the more legal and Tenant-right in equity and good Conſcience to renew the Leaſes of your ſaid Shops, him that hath paid a wrack rent of about 40 or 50 <hi>pounds per Annum</hi> for one ſingle Shop for 10 or 20 years together, or him that hath paid about 12 or 14 <hi>pounds per annum</hi> for the ſame tearm, and if you will not pleaſe to reſolve me in this queſtion, pray let it be propounded to the Antient Leaſees (when they come next before you with their humble petition for Leaſes of 21 years more) to give their anſwer thereunto, and it is prayed that their humble petition their Tenant-rights, and their 21 years Leaſes may out of your Court be diſmiſſed together. And as for an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement of their preſent rents, it is my humble requeſt unto
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171654:6"/>this Honourable Court (ſo long as they ſhall continue in actual poſſeſſion) that you would pleaſe to uſe them as kindly as you can.</p>
            <p>Having diſpatched the ancient Leaſees, I come now to the poor Sub-tenants, which preſent themſelves next in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and theſe I have placed in the Center, becauſe we uſually ſay, <hi>In Medio conſiſtit Virtus;</hi> ſo that I hope you will take ſpecial notice of them: But by reaſon I have alſo made bold to preſent you with an Humble Petition in their behalfs, (wherein their Caſe likewiſe is fairly and truely ſtated) and have prayed, that you would pleaſe to take them into your particular care and protection; I preſume I need not trouble you much further in this place, upon their Account.</p>
            <p>But onely there is one very material Objection and ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-block to be removed out of the way, before they can ſound a Victory, or can conclude, that their future Happineſs, Tranquillity and Redemption, is approaching, or near at hand, and that is this: <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That although you did formerly make a moſt famous Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (as being then truly ſenſible of the former Eſtate &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of your poor Sub-tenants) which if it was then made like the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> &amp; <hi>Perſians,</hi> unalterable, it deſerves to be engraven upon the Walls of your Royal Exchange, next to Sir <hi>William Turner,</hi> in Letters of Gold, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>That thoſe onely who ſhould be in actual Poſſeſſion at or near the Expiration of any of your future Leaſes, ſhould be permitted to Renew.</q>
            <p>But ſo it is, That ſince the late dreadfull Fire, this Order hath been much infringed, and you have taken 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> a piece of ſeveral of the ancient Leaſees, to Renew again for Eleven years (ſo that, <hi>Tempora mutantur,</hi> &amp; New Lords, New Laws.) But it is hoped, that upon ſecond thoughts, and upon your Petitioners preſent Complaint, you will not permit them to Renew; but will ſtill conſtrue this Tranſaction, with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171654:7"/>reference and reſpect firſt had to your former Order, unleſs you did repeal and make void the ſaid Order after the late Fire, and before you did receive their ſaid Five pounds, or elſe that you did not take any notice thereof, as not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring in what a Condition thoſe Sub-tenants had been; or elſe that you took it for granted, that all thoſe Leaſees; who had payd in their Five pounds, had been in actual poſſeſſion; and if ſo, you may very well return them their Money again, as under a miſtake: But if this for the preſent cannot be avoyded, it is hoped for the future (as Leaſes do fall into your hands) you will pleaſe to take a ſpecial and particular care in relation thereunto.</p>
            <p>And now it comes into my mind, I remember a remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Paſſage of an ancient Shop-keeper (as I have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) of your <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> which being pertinent to the buſineſs in hand, I have thought good here to inſert, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the good old Man having payd a Wrack-rent for the ſpace of ſeveral years together, for his Dwelling-houſe, but at length, when his Land-lords Leaſe from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany was near expired, as he was ſitting one Night by the Fire, with his Children about him, there knocks a man at his door with this Meſſage, <hi>viz.</hi> That he came from the Maſter and Wardens of ſuch a Company, to give him No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that he muſt come ſuch a day to the Hall (as being the immediate Tenant) to Renew the Leaſe of his Houſe: At which the good old Man was ſo much overjoyed and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, as that he thought it was a good Angel in Humane ſhape, that did appear to bring him ſuch welcome and ſuch acceptable Tydings. The Application hereof I leave to your moſt worthy ſelves; and if it ſhould ſo happen, that in proceſs of time, Mr. <hi>Godfrey,</hi> or any of your Officers, ſhould chance to be any of theſe good Angels, I queſtion not but the honeſt and true-hearted Sub-tenants, would give them honeſt content and ſatisfaction for their pains.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:171654:7"/>
            <p>And now to cloſe, in relation to theſe Sub-tenants, I do verily believe that many of them are but in a mean and low Condition: And the truth of it is, what with the Rent for their Houſes, what with the Charge for their Families, what with the loſs in Braded Wares, what with the Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faſhions, (but only this is an Age of Wonders, or elſe one might well ſtand amazed, and be aſtoniſhed, at the moſt prodigious Humour, and ſtrange fickleneſs of the Age upon this very Account,) what with deſperate Debts, and what with bad Trading, they need not have wrack Land-lords, (if poſſibly to be avoyded;) for furious Lievtenants to bring up the Rear (unleſs Trading ſhould thereupon flow in upon them like a mighty flood) in order to their more ſpeedy, and ſometimes moſt certain Ruine.</p>
            <p>And when men are in Durance, Bondage and Slavery, for them to uſe all fair and probable Means whereby to Redeem themſelves out of the ſaid Captivity, I think this is no Sin, nor Offence either to God or Man. But the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Leaſees will not admit, nor by no means ſwallow this down for Orthodox Doctrine, and will ſay, That thoſe who go about, and are Inſtrumental in deſtroying of their Tenant-rights, and their intereſt in future Leaſes, (the which, with the Locks, Shackles and Fetters which they have put upon them, they do think are as good both to them and their Heirs, as Land of Inheritance) do deſerve to be ſeverely and exemplarily chaſtiſed: But whether the ancient Leaſees, or the poor Sub-tenants Doctrine in this particular, be true or falſe, <hi>Sub Judice lis eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to proceed to my Third and laſt Enterprize, <hi>viz.</hi> To the Outward Pawn-tenants: And as I have placed the ancient Leaſees in the front of the Battel, that ſo they may lead the Van, (and becauſe I humbly conceive they have been the <hi>Duces omnium malorum,</hi> of all theſe late Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities, I have thereupon thought good to put them into the Forlorn Hope, and peradventure upon that Account, if
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171654:8"/>they ſhould chance to meet with a brisk Rencounter before the Grand Committee, it is probable they may come off with broken Pates, or which is worſe, with the loſs of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of their limbs; that is, with the loſs of ſome branches of their future and wrack-rented Revenues;) ſo I have placed the Sub-tenants in the Center, hoping thereby (being now ſhrowded under your ſafeguard and protection) there they may be ſafe and ſecure enough from the Annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and danger of the Enemy. And now as to your Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Pawn-tenants, although they come laſt in Order, yet they ſtand in the Second place of Honour, whereupon I am reſolved to make theſe my Noble Lievtenants, and do not queſtion but they may prove valiant Champions to bring up the Rear.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the men therefore <hi>(Right Honourable and Right Worſhipful)</hi> who came lately out of the Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> (pray pardon the ſimilitude and all others of the like nature as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing added only by way of illuſtration) and were redeemed from their Captivity therein by your moſt valiant and noble hands, in hopes that in a ſhort time you would have placed them in a Land flowing with Milk &amp; Honey, but ſo it is (may it pleaſe your good Lordſhip and Worſhips) that by the inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious influence of ſome ſuperior Planets being predominant or by ſome other unlucky interpoſition (for they know not where certainly to fix it, although I could here give a ſhrewd gueſs as to the true cauſe and reaſon thereof) they do find themſelves ſtill in the Wilderneſs, and are at this time in their Journey no farther than the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> and as for their daily ſuſtenance they cry out for help, help (and it is you Right Honourable, and you Right Worſhipfull, and you onely, that can work a Miracle for them) or elſe in a ſhort time, they ſay, they ſhall famiſh in this barren Wilderneſs for want of Bread, they mean for want of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, by reaſon of the Inconveniences of their preſent ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:171654:8"/>
            <p>But yet once again, theſe are the Men (Right Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and Right Worſhipfull) which have liſted themſelves under your Protection; theſe are the Men that have march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under your Conduct, and have obeyed your Commands: theſe are the men that have fought your Battles, (that is, vindicated your Honour upon all Occaſions, in building this moſt ſtately, and moſt magnificent Structure of the Royal Exchange, and of your building double Pawns therein:) Theſe are the Men who have kept poſſeſſion of your Shops (although to ſome of them a moſt apparent loſs and diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; witneſs in particular, by name Mr. <hi>William Rutland ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior,</hi>) when others of a more puſillanimous and faint-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpirit, upon their firſt entrance into the Battle did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately quit the field, (returning again to their Garlick and Onions) and left their fellow-ſouldiers to ſhift for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and yet notwithſtanding maugre all the reproach and contempt that have been caſt upon your Outward Pawns, (ſuch as, <hi>By-Walks, Turn-again-lanes, Back-ſide of Mother Browns Barn,</hi> and the like; but you may gueſs from whence theſe Appellations came, and to what end deſigned,) have ſtill ſtoutly held out (although ſo ſtrongly begirt with ſuch ſtrong and potent Aſſailants) in hopes that relief would come in its proper ſeaſon, and that muſt be when you are poſſeſſed with a clear underſtanding of the right of their Caſe, and of the reaſon of things, and then ſurely you are Obliged in Honour (conſidering all theſe precedent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances) to rally up your Forces to raiſe the ſiege, and to relieve your Garriſon, and that with all Expedition, leſt that they ſhould be ſo put to their ſhifts, as that they could not hold out much longer, but muſt be forced to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der up your Fort Royall upon diſhonourable terms, and ſo in concluſion be made Priſoners of War. And this may now commodiouſly be done (for it lies within your power, <hi>de facto,</hi> at preſent, to effect the ſame,) by anſwering their Expectations, by ſatisfying their Deſires, by granting their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171654:9"/>Petitions, and by hearkning to their Propoſals whenever they ſhall make Application unto you, wherein your publick Intereſt ſhall be concerned, as well as their own Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency and Accommodation.</p>
            <p>But inaſmuch as theſe Outward Pawn-tenants, have at this day a Petition before you, with Reaſons annexed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, wherein they have ſtated their own preſent Caſe, (and I cannot imagine who can ſtate their own Caſe, or ſhew where their ſhooes pinch them, better than themſelves) unto their ſaid Petition and Reaſons therefore I ſhall at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent moſt humbly refer you.</p>
            <p>And in the mean time, inaſmuch as in my Introduction I gave you a hint, that I would not conceal any thing from you, either for fear or favour, as material to my preſent purpoſe, or neceſſary for your Information; give me leave then in purſuance thereof, here to repreſent unto you ſome of their private Whiſperings, and preſent Sentiments, when they do uſually meet together upon theſe publick Concerns; the which being duly weighed, conſidered and digeſted, among your worthy ſelves, for ought I know it may prove here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after of ſingular Uſe, Benefit and Advantage, for the publick intereſt of your <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And wherein theſe Tenants of yours have Reaſon on their ſide, I hope you will pleaſe to give me leave to ſay ſomething in their Vindication; but if not, I ſhall be as free on the other hand to declaim againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimis</hi> therefore, <hi>&amp; ante omnia,</hi> They do ſay, that ever ſince they did petition the Grand Committee for double Pawns (they mean that Committee, who were firſt appointed for Re-building of the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi>) inaſmuch as it hath not anſwered all thoſe Ends and Purpoſes, as to the Income and Revenue which at firſt they did deſign thereby, ſome of the ſaid Members (and who are yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued) have had ſome prejudice againſt them upon that very Account; And whenever ſince they have made any
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171654:9"/>humble Propoſal, in order to the general and publick Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the ſaid Place, or for their own Convenience and Accommodation, they do find that this hath alwayes been a blot in their Eſcutcheons, as to their Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof; For ſome of the ſaid Members uſually riſing up and declaring, That theſe were the Men that did firſt petition them for Double Pawns; ſo that they have been conſtrained to go home again much diſcontented, ſince all hath been daſhed upon this account: So that in Anſwer hereunto, I muſt needs enter my Proteſt, and ſay, That theſe Gentlemen are ſomewhat too partial in relation thereunto; for although theſe Tenants of yours did petition for double Pawns, yet ſurely they did not impoſe upon the Committee in their ſo doing; for doubtleſs they did follow the Dictates of their own Reaſons and Apprehenſions, notwithſtanding their ſaid Petition; And this doth plainly appear by the Conſequence thereof, for in many things they have gone quite contrary to their ſaid Petition; and if they had not, they never would have troubled the Court afterwards ſo often as they have done, to make ſome convenient Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the ſaid Place. And although before the late moſt dreadfull Fire, there were too ſmall a number of ſmall Shops therein, and it was a very great ſhame and diſparagement, to ſee your <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> cut and mangled, divided and ſub-divided, into halves, quarters, and three-quarter Shops, and at ſuch an exceſſive Rate alſo, as that it was almoſt impoſſible for any Perſon to live comfortably therein; ſo now (as the matter hath been ordered) there is on the other hand, too great a number of ſmall Shops therein: But as Double Pawns were modeſtly propoſed (though not impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) and had it taken Effect, there would not have been one ſmall Shop too many at this day in the ſaid place. And here under this Head, I will not omit one thing more, which they do ſay (and peradventure may be one occult Reaſon why their modeſt Propoſals have been alwayes ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171654:10"/>much ſlighted and contemned) <hi>viz.</hi> That ſome leading Members of this Honourable Court, have taken a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar prejudice and diſpleaſure againſt one of your Outward-Pawn Tenants, (and that clearly upon a miſtake, and a falſe Report) in a buſineſs, wherein as to matter of Fact he was as innocent as the Child that is yet unborn.</p>
            <p>But to proceed a little further, (for things of this and the like nature coming to light, may at length turn to ſome good Account;) in the next place they do ſay, That when they did lately petition for the turning of the Stairs on the North-ſide, and for ſome other convenient Alterations to be made in your Outward Pawns, whereby they might in ſome meaſure be equally accommodated with the reſt of their Neighbours, the Committee did not deal ſo fairly, candidly, and openly with them, as was expected:</p>
            <p>For when they came firſt before them, there came ſome perſons alſo of the inward Pawn (who it ſeems had heard of their intentions) and deſired of the Court that they would pleaſe to give them admiſſion into their preſence, that ſo they might hear the ſaid propoſals for alterations, as well as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but being asked the queſtion, whether they came there by virtue of any power or authority from the reſt of their Neighbours, their anſwer was in the Negative, but however as to their deſire, the Court asking the petitioners whether they were willing thereunto, whoſe anſwer was in the Affirmative (but with a proviſo) they were immediately admitted thereupon, and upon the hearing and debate of the ſaid propoſals, the Court told them; that if they would come hand in hand by a joynt conſent, their buſineſs was half done, for they ſaid they would do any thing in reaſon for the general good of the whole Exchange, and therefore they did adviſe thoſe inward Pawn Gentlemen to return a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain unto the place from whence they came, and to conſult with their principals, and aſſemble their Neighbours toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and come again as authorized from them, with argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171654:10"/>againſt the ſaid propoſals, and then they mould be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heard, And as for the outward Pawn Tenants they told them that they need not come again in a body, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two or three of them deputed from the whole, would be ſufficient to come and receive an anſwer to their humble peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereupon they went away very well ſatisfied for that time, with ſo fair, ſo modeſt, and ſo generous an anſwer; but it ſeems it was to fair weather to laſt long, for behold imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately afterwards came this approaching ſtorm, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Court day comes Mr. <hi>Rutland,</hi> Mr. <hi>Duke,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Henry Joyce,</hi> (according to the Courts own order and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment) with full power and authority, from the reſt of their Neighbours (under their own hands, which they did produce in Court) to repreſent the whole. But no perſons came from the inward Pawn (for at that time and at preſent, the major part of the Royal Exchange will not be againſt convenient alterations, but only ſome particular men who are particularly concerned in the inward Pawns) whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Court did immediately ſend for the perſons aforeſaid to come before them, but no commiſſion yet could they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, neither had they (according to the Courts advice) aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled their Neighbours, but only kept a very great clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and herein it is obſervable that they were called in ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately from the reſt, although before the other party were very free and willing to admit of them joyntly to make their defence. But when Arguments cannot do, then Policy muſt; and this they knew full well, that your ſaid Tenants if they might be permitted to be heard, were able to anſwer to every iota, tittle, and point, which they ſhould alledge in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto the ſaid alterations.</p>
            <p>But however the Court did diſmiſs the ſaid outward Pawn Tenants very abruptly at that time, but withal that it was very probable they might farther conſider of their ſaid propoſals, if they would ſtill come hand in hand, whereas as they went home together with thoſe inward Pawn Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171654:11"/>and going to the Tavern afterwards to drink a glaſs of Wine together, (which was kindly done of them all not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their oppoſition ſo furiouſly one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) one of them rounded his Companion in the eare, but it muſt be a very great ſecret, and under the Roſe alſo (and as we uſually ſay <hi>in vino veritas</hi>) viz. That they might ſet their hearts at reſt and be quiet, for the Committee had faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully promiſed them that they would make no alterations, whereupon they were ſo diſſatisfied and diſcontented, that they ſay, they have great cauſe to take it unkindly from the Court, this their unkind and unexpected dealings with them, and that they did then reſolve never to trouble the Court more, upon that accompt, or upon any other accompt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. And theſe very men have as little reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain for want of a trade as any perſons in the Exchange whatſoever, only they thought, that by the turning of the Stairs on the Northſide, ſome water might have run by their Mills which made them ſo eager and furious in oppoſition thereunto, whereas if their Shops ſtood in one of the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Morefields</hi> next <hi>Bedlam</hi> gate (in the way that they deal in) they could not miſs of Trade (and plain dealing is beſt, although the crafty Politician ſayes that he that uſes it will dye a begger.) And here farther they do ſay, that when at any time they come into your Court, they muſt obſerve that diſtance, they muſt ſo place their words, they muſt obſerve that order and method in their deportment, for fear of diſpleaſing ſome Member or other, who will immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately repute them either ſaucy, peremptory or too pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, that your eyes being ſo much upon them (and many times they ſay they are catcht up before they are down,) they have ſuch an awe and dread upon their Spirits, for fear of giving offence, ſo that many times they cannot ſay what they would, and have to ſay, upon this very accompt. Whereas one would think in reaſon, that Landlords ſhould be as free to permit their Tenants to ſpeak to them in all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171654:11"/>caſes whatſoever (paying the due reſpects which they owe unto the quality of their perſons, and to the place where they are aſſembled in Court) as they are free to receive their rents from their ſaid Tenants. And although ſometimes it may fall out that a man may take a bargain of his Landlord, as that his Houſe, his Land, or Shop, may be very well worth and better than the Money that he pays for the ſame, yet your preſent Tenants do ſay (and I am very apt to believe them therein,) that their Money is far better at preſent, (nay dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the value, as I ſhall make it appear hereafter by undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reaſons) than any of yours ſaid Shops, So that upon the whole matter, I dare engage in the behalf of all your outward Pawn Tenants (here and there one only excepted which do drive very conſiderable Trades) that in regard of thoſe moſt unavoidable circumſtances and inconveniencies which do alwaies attend the ſaid place (many whereof are hinted in the Sub-Tenants caſe) if any of them could get elſe where but 100 <hi>pounds per Annum</hi> a peice, towards the preſent ma in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of themſelves and Families, they would then ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way bid adieu to all their concerns within your Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change. And this (if ſeriouſly weighed and conſidered) is a miſerable caſe, that a man muſt be conſtrained to give his conſtant attendance in the ſaid place, and yet (in regard of the ſaid inconveniencies) ſhall not be able to get 100 <hi>pounds per annum</hi> for his preſent maintenance, and yet when it is got (although out of the fire too, becauſe the place at preſent is more like <hi>Birchin lane,</hi> than a Royal Exchange) the one moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof muſt go, towards the payment of his Landlords for his houſe and Shop.</p>
            <p>And if this be their preſent caſe, and if this were the late proceedings of the Court againſt them, alas! poor men what ſhall I ſay, Where will they center at laſt in hopes of releif, and when will the time come, wherein they may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, that their halcion daies are approaching, and that they may lift up their Heads, for their redemption draweth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171654:12"/>nigh. And now a little to plead their cauſe upon the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent circumſtances. As to matter of Alterations, all men in the world will allow this to be reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> That you ſhould endeavour to make both your Pawns as Equal as poſſibly you can, for the general Accommodation of the whole, (inaſmuch as all are equally and alike concerned, as to matter of Rents,) or elſe, that you ſhould make ſuch a proportionable Abatement and Allowance, according to the real and apparent difference of the ſaid place.</p>
            <p>But for ſome men to perſwade you, That in making any convenient Alterations (ſuch as Turning the Stairs, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king down the Poſts on the North-ſide, and making the Eaſt and Weſt-ſide into Large Shops, and the like,) would deſtroy and impair your Inward Pawn-Rents, (which it ſeems was their grand Objection, and the Committee did ſwallow it without chewing) is ſuch a Wind-mill and a Chimaera, as I could eaſily make it appear, (onely ſelf-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt men will put on a good face upon any thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, though never ſo incongruous and inconſiſtent with Humane Reaſon, and as we proverbially ſay, <hi>Audaces For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna juvat, cùm in terga removetur Modeſtia,</hi>) That I muſt here moſt earneſtly beſeech your good Lordſhip and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, that you would not henceforward ſuffer your ſelves (by any prevailing Party, or pretence whatſoever) to be born down with the Clamours and Railings, but with the Reaſons of Men: For if you ſhould make at this day what Alterations you pleaſe, without the conſent and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Ancient and Modern Leaſees (for they were both Modern which came then before you) or being fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their Bug-bears, or allured with their Charms, as to the danger that may enſue thereby; yet it is Ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds to a Nut-ſhell, but the preſent Inhabitants and Sub-tenants of the ſaid inward Pawns, (wherein there is at preſent above Three-ſcore of your ſaid Shops let upon the Wrack,) may be brought over and perſwaded by very good
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171654:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>words to accept of your Leaſes (when they are expired) at your preſent Rents, if in caſe hereafter it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that you cannot poſſibly afford them at a cheaper Rate.</p>
            <p>And moreover ſome of them do likewiſe ſay, That the Walks of your <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> are ſo extream and pitifull Narrow, ſo that both the <hi>Exchanges</hi> at the other end of the Town (and many times their Cuſtomers by way of Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for their reſpects and value they have for thoſe <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes,</hi> take notice thereof) do far ſurpaſs and outvie them upon that very Account. And again ſome do ſay, (which although it be a jocular and a pleaſant Reaſon, yet there may be much of truth therein) <hi>viz.</hi> That by reaſon the Stairs of your <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> are built ſo high, they have of late, loſt moſt of their Tiſſical, Conſumptive and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winded Cuſtomers within the City of <hi>London,</hi> and Suburbs thereof, (the which being of ſo vaſt an extent, and a place ſo Populous, may ariſe to a very great number) which in <hi>Greſham Colledge</hi> was a conſiderable branch of their preſent Revenue.</p>
            <p>And here by the way, Had you made your Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for ſuch ſmall Trades as are now in your <hi>Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> below ſtairs, in thoſe extream parts which you have purchaſed and taken in, but bring you in nothing conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable (by reaſon you would not have it ſtand contiguous, in order to the greater ſafety and ſecurity for the future of the ſaid place) and that the ſaid Shops ſhould have fronted towards the Merchants (with double Pillars, although they are now but ſingle) juſt as it was in <hi>Greſham-Colledge;</hi> and alſo, that you had made above ſtairs but one long ſingle Pawn, and but one Roof, with large and deep Shops there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, fitting for <hi>Mercers, Silk-men, Indian-gown</hi> Men, <hi>Popes-head-Alley</hi> Men, and all other whole-ſale Men of the preſent Inhabitants as have occaſion (by reaſon of their Trades) to make uſe of large Shops, you had then made it the moſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171654:13"/>famous place for Accommodation of Trades, this day in the whole World: And it would have brought you in what Revenue you had pleaſed in Reaſon to require for the ſame. And if the City of <hi>London,</hi> and Right Worſhipfull Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Mercers,</hi> ſhould condeſcend ſo far, as to ſpare (or to procure) ſo much Money whereby to make it ſtill after the ſame Manner (the Conſent of all Parties concerned being firſt had and obtained) I dare forfeit all the Concerns I have in the World, (in regard I am able to make it out by moſt ſolid, ſubſtantial rational demonſtrations) that in ſeven years time it would turn to Account. And if this can be made out, then lay your hands to the Plough yet once again, and the Lord proſper the work of your hands, and your handy-work. But I fear, ſhould this but once be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, both the <hi>Exchanges</hi> at the other end of the Town, would immediately petition the Parliament to put a ſtop to your proceedings therein, and alſo that they would pleaſe to make an Act, That your <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> ſhould hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward remain and be continued for ever in the ſame Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Form as it is at this day, any Law, Statute, Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Proviſo, or By-law, to the contrary, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I do verily believe, that the Merchants of <hi>London,</hi> if once propoſed unto them, would be willing to contribute their proportions (and that in a very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meaſure) for their particular Accommodations. And for my own part, were I for to take my choyce, I had much rather give you 30 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum</hi> for one ſingle Shop below ſtairs, of Eight Foot, ſo accommodated, than give you Five pounds <hi>per annum</hi> for one Shop above of the ſame Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions; and I could wiſh with all my heart, that ſome worthy, wealthy and moſt Noble Citizen, that in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Premiſes, (which would be ſo much to his Honour, and to his everlaſting praiſe and renown) would pleaſe to make his own hands his preſent Executors, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171654:13"/>would preſent you with a Bag of Gold of Twenty or Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand pounds, to be expended after this Manner, and would but make me one of his Surveyers and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers of the Work; I would then not only forfeit all my Concerns, but my Life it ſelf, if I did not make your <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in a ſhort time, the moſt Famous, moſt Noble (ſetting aſide the magnificence of the Structure, which you have already accompliſhed) and moſt Renowned place for Accommodation of Trades, as any place this day under the cope of Heaven. Pray pardon this ſmall digreſſion of mine, although it ſhould never turn to any Account. But in good earneſt, (and I do moſt ſolemnly here proteſt, in confirmation thereof) that had I ſuch an Eſtate as many of our wealthy and worthy Citizens have, of ſome Thirty or Forty thouſand pounds a Man, I would willingly (with all my Soul) advance the one Moiety (for the Honour of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the Glory of the Nation) in order to the Accompliſhment thereof. But to proceed:</p>
            <p>Theſe outward Pawn Tenants (notwithſtanding their former bad ſucceſs) have it ſeems adventured to preſent themſelves before you yet once more, as being of late ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated and encouraged thereunto by ſome worthy Members of this Grand Committee, in particular, by name, Mr. War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>Godfrey:</hi> So that you ſee they are willing to embrace any Opportunity, to take hold on every Twig to ſave themſelves, that ſo at laſt they may arrive at their deſired Haven. But it ſeems it is not at preſent (by reaſon of their former ill ſucceſs) for any Alterations, (although that would be in ſome caſes eſſentially neceſſary to the future Benefit and Advantage of the whole Exchange) but for a general Abatement of their preſent Rents. But what with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of ſome predominant and prevailing Party, what with the former prejudice and miſinformation of ſome of your own worthy Members, what with the Clamors and Railings of ſome particular and ſelf-intereſted perſons,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171654:14"/>(whoſe Eyes will be evil, becauſe peradventure yours may be good,) eſpecially the ancient Leaſees: They do not know how they ſhall ſpeed, or what good ſucceſs they ſhall have therein, onely they do hope, that ſince that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee is changed, your Reſolutions may not be the ſame, and that they may ſay, <hi>Tempora mutantur, &amp; vos mutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini in illis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now in conſideration of the Premiſes, and upon the whole matter therein contained, peradventure you may here reply and ſay, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That thoſe Perſons whoſe particular Intereſts I have here undertaken, have certainly obliged themſelves by ſome particular Contract and Agreement, or elſe by ſome verbal Promiſes, to preſent you with ſome large and Noble Preſent and Gratuity for your pains and Expences, or elſe doubtleſs you would never have ſo zealouſly, and ſo paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately eſpouſed (as you have done in this <hi>Memorial</hi> now preſented unto us) their Cauſe therein.</p>
            <p>But as to this, I will <hi>extempore</hi> and directly anſwer to the matter in hand, and will aſſure your good Lordſhip and Worſhips, <hi>(&amp; verbo Chriſtiani verum eſt,)</hi> That there is no one Perſon within the walls of your <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> (as an Inhabitant thereof) that hath made any ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Contract, Agreement, or any verbal Promiſe with me upon that Account, nor but two of them (before it went to the Preſs) that I ever gave any hint of my Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Reſolutions therein, in order thereunto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But as to matter of Alterations, it is very probable you may here alſo reply and ſay, That you are in ſome meaſure ſatisfied with the Reaſons thereof (although the former Committees hitherto have been born down therein by the prevalency of parties, and for want of a true information of the right of the Caſe) and that thereupon you are reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to take that and the poor Sub-Tenants Caſe together very ſuddenly (and that upon mature deliberation) into your
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171654:14"/>moſt ſollemn and ſerious conſiderations, &amp; that you will take all the care imaginable for the future, that the innocent ſhall be protected, that the oppreſſor ſhall be diſcountenanced, and that the honeſt and plain hearted (though modeſt and baſhful) ſhall be encouraged and emboldened to ſpeak their own Sentiments: and that all your Tenants in general (who are immediate poſſeſſors) ſhall be ſo fairly, and ſo nobly treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by an equal accommodation, that they ſhall have no cauſe to complain hence forward, the one againſt the other; and if this be your anſwer hereunto I do here in their behalfs preſent you with my moſt humble and hearty thanks. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. As to any general abatement of their preſent rents <hi>(durus est hic ſermo)</hi> it is ſuch a thing, ſuch an hard matter to ſwallow down, as cannot poſſibly enter as yet, not ſo much as into your private thoughts (as you are choſen truſtees) for performance thereof, inaſmuch as there lyes ſuch a grand weight and ſtrong objection againſt it, as that it is as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble almoſt to remove Mountains, as it is to remove the ſaid objection out of the way, and although you are convinced and ſatisfied, that your Tenants <hi>(rebus ſic ſtantibus)</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſeveral circumſtances and inconveniences herein ſo largely declared, ought to ſit but at very moderate rents, yet untill ſome of the outward or inward Pawn Tenants can ſolve this objection and remove it out of the way; you muſt turn your deafears unto the charmer (as you have here ſo powerfully endeavoured) although he ſhould charm never ſo loud, and the objection <hi>(in paucis Verbis)</hi> is this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> That you have kept a very fair accompt of the whole charge of your rebuilding the Royal Exchange, and in the ſumme total, you do find it doth amount unto a very great ſumme, and that you have no other way or meane whereby to reimburſe your ſelves, but upon the preſent in habitants of the ſaid place, wherein you have taken ſuch care ſo to moderate and proportion the rents and the rates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your Shops therein, according to the computation of you
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171654:15"/>charge, deſiring but a very little more by an annual rent and future revenue for the ſame, than the bare intereſt of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney doth amount unto (the principal ſtill remaining within the walls of the ſaid building) ſo that you cannot poſſibly afford your Shops at a cheaper rate than at preſent you do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for them.</p>
            <p>This objection (I muſt confeſs) ſeems ſo fair, ſo equitable, and ſo reaſonable at the very firſt appearance that one would think it were enough (without any farther progreſs) to ſtop the mouths of all perſons whatſoever, from making any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions upon the members of the grand Committee for their putting ſuch a preſent rate upon their ſaid Shops. And I muſt confeſs I ſhould be here very unwilling to enter the liſts, whereby to ſolve this objection or to give any anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, ſo far forth as to give the City and Company any offence therein, yet if they would pleaſe to give me leave, ſo far as if I were one of their preſent Tenants (and peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I have been formerly ſomewhat related unto the ſaid place) I would then ſo ſcan this objection, by taking it in pieces, and off from the hinges, as that I do not queſtion but I ſhould make it appear, in a far different dreſs, and although in my anſwer I expect no offence to be taken on the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies ſide, yet as to the City ſide if I make it appear, by dint of argument and by undeniable reaſons: that they may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford their ſaid Shops at a great deal cheaper rate, than at preſent they do; I hope then (as they are perſons of honour, and intelligent agents, and ſo conſequently men indued with reaſon and underſtanding) they will immediately fall down, and be captivated with the moſt ſweet and harmonious voice of her powerful charms.</p>
            <p>And here by the way, before I come directly to the matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hand, (<hi>viz.</hi> to the more ſollid and ſubſtantial part of my reſent undertaking) I think it not impertinent, but rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery requiſite and neceſſary (in order to prepare your minds unto a more gentle and eaſie reception of the ſubſequent ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171654:15"/>to put you in mind and by way of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance to repreſent unto you, how that many worthy Perſons, and worthy Citizens, (as well as your ſelves) have ſince the late dreadful fire (in order to the rebuilding of the City of <hi>London,</hi> out of a noble and publique Spirit, becauſe they would not have it remain and lye ſtill buried in its own Aſhes, but (like the <hi>Phaenix</hi> out of its flames) would rather contribute their aſſiſtance and endeavours, to have it raiſed again with more beauty and luſtre than formerly) have laid out many thouſand pounds, in building of Houſes and Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes; and other conveniencies for the accompliſhment thereof: but yet when theſe accommodations have been built by them. What with the deadneſs of Trading, what with the Poverty of the Inhabitants, (as having not yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered their great loſſes, by reaſon of the late Conflagration) what with the inconvenience of the Scituation of the ſaid Houſes, or of the inconvenience of the building of them as not commodious and fitting for Merchants in the place where they ſtand, and what by reaſon of putting too great a rate upon them at the firſt, (and this is enough in all conſcience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to marr all their primary and publick intentions what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſover, and then no marvel that they have had no better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs) and the like: They have been ſo much blown upon, as that at laſt they have been glad to take what they could get in reaſon (which they might have had at the firſt) for the ſame, and thereby have been ſuch conſiderable looſers (whereas they might have been ſufficient gainers) as that I do believe they have not made 4 <hi>per Cent.</hi> for the laying out of their Monies. And you cannot be ignorant likewiſe how that many hundreds of Landlords in the Country have of late years had their Farms thrown up into their hands, and their Tenants have been in arrears for Rent, ſome two, and ſome three years together, (although you endeavour to receive yours every quarter, and are the beſt rents in the world, were they once moderated with a <hi>quantum meruit</hi>) and by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171654:16"/>reaſon of the badneſs of Trade and Corn not yeilding a price, their ſaid Land-lords have been conſtrained to take what they could get, and that ſometimes hath not been the one Moiety; and to take an extreme Courſe againſt them, hath been but a weak Refuge; (for it was never yet known, that a Priſon could work ſuch a Miracle, as to pay Debts when the Perſon hath it not) and afterwards have let them to other Tenants at a far leſs Price, or to them again with a very conſiderable Abatement. The Application hereof, I leave to your worthy ſelves.</p>
            <p>And here I am heartily glad, that I need not go far for a proof of this point, inaſmuch as I can produce two no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and moſt famous Inſtances within the walls of your moſt ſtately and moſt magnificent Fabrick, for confirmation hereof: The one is of a moderate and Noble Leaſee, by name Mr. <hi>Edward Carleton,</hi> (pray let him not be named or ranked among the precedent ones, unleſs it be for a Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and a good Example to all thoſe as ſhall hereafter arrive unto the ſame pitch of Honour as to be ancient Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees) who rather than he would ſtay for a Cuſtomer to give him 150 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> Fine, and 100 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum,</hi> for one of your great Shops (which was your firſt Market-price) hath let it ſince, as I am informed, unto honeſt Mr. <hi>Stephen Proctor,</hi> for leſs than 40 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum.</hi> The other Inſtance is of your moſt worthy ſelves, in your Noble and generous condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, in Letting of late, (although formerly you might have had a far better price, but it was then refuſed) a Shop of the ſame dimenſions, for or near the ſame rate. So that from hence I may very well argue with you both wayes, <hi>viz.</hi> Either <hi>à majore ad minus, aut à minore ad majus,</hi> from theſe two great Shops, to the reſt of the ſmall Shops proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably, or elſe from this ſmall and generous <hi>Exordium,</hi> untill you ſhall have paſſed through the whole entire Body of your <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> and ſo by degrees happily meet again (where you ſo fairly began) by the ſame Noble and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171654:16"/>Concluſion. And that you may the rather be excited hereunto, and not any longer ſuffer your ſaid place to ſtand upon this tottering and ſandy foundation, ſome of you may very well remember what a precaution and early advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment this Honourable Court had given them by the aforeſaid Authour of that Book called <hi>Londons Nonſuch</hi> (the which the Leaſees out of the ſingular favour, love and reſpect which they bore unto his Perſon, or rather unto the Antient and good old cauſe of wrack rents, or ſome other good cauſes and conſiderations them thereunto moving, were pleaſed to ſtile <hi>Londons Nonſence.</hi>) In theſe words. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Take heed leſt by your Rents and Fines you build not on the Sand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely he ſaw then ſomething beforehand, which it ſeems hath ſince came to paſs in a very great meaſure.</p>
            <p>And O! the miſerable effects and moſt dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents in all matters and things either in Eccleſiaſtical or temporal affairs whatſoever, in winding and ſcrueing them up to the higheſt pitch, and it is ten to one, but in ſuch proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and tranſactions they do marr and break all at the laſt: whereas were there a mediocrity and a mean uſed in all theſe concerns, things then would run in a far clearer and more Cryſtal Channel, and the world it ſelf would be at a far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paſs, than it is at this day.</p>
            <p>And as I remember one of the Kings of <hi>France</hi> once, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding his Secretary to write down the beſt ſingle word that ever he read in his life, he immediately (in obedience to his Majeſties pleaſure) writes down this word, <hi>viz. MODE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is no more nor no leſs than what we are all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned and commanded upon ſacred record, in theſe plain and intelligible words, <hi>viz.</hi> Let your Moderation be known unto all Men, &amp;c. And truly for all men who are intelligent agents, <hi>et ergo</hi> rational Creatures, to be modeſt, humble and courteous in all their affairs and tranſactions whatſoever, is a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171654:17"/>moſt laudable, commendable and a moſt excellent vertue (like Dame nature her ſelf, who is moderate in all her deſires, and when over charged we do but put her out of her courſe and diſturb her, and ſhe takes it as a very great affront and injury offered unto her worthy ſelf) And how many Perſons are there now at this day, yet ſurviving within the limits and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories of his Majeſties Realms and Dominions, who were formerly in Power and Authority, and for want of making uſe of this thing called Moderation, did mar and break all their deſigns and enterprizes whatſoever, and did ſplit themſelves upon the Rock of Extremity and Preſumption, as little dreaming there might come a day of an Accompt? and if a man had been inſpired from Heaven in thoſe dayes, with the Spirit of Prophecy, (although many times by natural reaſon, one may give a ſhrewd gueſs of ſubſequent conſequences, by precedent circumſtances) and had gone to them and told them: Gentlemen, my humble requeſt unto you is, that you would pleaſe to let your Moderation be known unto all Men, for my Lord the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty is near at hand, I warrant you ſuch a Perſon would have been eſteemed moſt ridiculous, impertinent, fanatical and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible.</p>
            <p>But if they had taken it into their ſerious thoughts and conſiderations, and thereupon had embraced Moderation, they would not have ſuffered ſo much reproach &amp; contempt in their honour and reputation, as ſome of them (I do pity them with all my heart) have done ſince his Majeſties Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And for any perſon whatſoever now adays to make any reflection upon any particular perſon, by reaſon of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer in advertency and miſcarriage herein, it is an unworthy and inbecoming action, and ſure I am, no ſober mind would do it; inaſmuch as there is an act of indempnity paſſed by King, Lords and Commons to have all theſe things buried in the embers of Oblivion and forgetfulneſs, and that they would have no diſtinction of Perſons now uſed, ſave only
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171654:17"/>what conſiſts with the Longitude and Latitude of a good Chriſtian, a good Subject, and a good Citizen; and in the Country, a good Common-Wealths man, that is ſuch a one as doth ſtudy the common good and benefit of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and of all the parts adjacent where he ſhall or may ſurvive. And becauſe many of theſe Men (who otherwiſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry intelligent) may be now heartily ſorry for their miſtakes, and if in caſe they were in the ſame capacity, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver run again the ſame extremes, and I could wiſh(with all my heart) that theſe books that are now in print, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to be ſold (which do ſo much reflect upon theſe mens Credit and Reputation) were not tollerated, inaſmuch as it is (in my ſlender apprehenſion) a direct breach of the ſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and act of Grace which doth ſo ſtrictly prohibit and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the ſame.</p>
            <p>But all this is as yet beſides the matter in hand, and not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to the point (although I hope they may be of ſome uſe and benefit in ſome caſes), for the ſtrength of the Objection lyes herein; <hi>viz.</hi> That you have laid out ſo much money al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready upon the rebuilding of your Royal Exchange, and that in reaſon you ought to have ſo much intereſt for the ſame by way of improvement, or elſe you might as well have thrown away your Money into the Streets, or have ſent it into the Iſland of <hi>terra incognita</hi> for a venture, and it would have turned to the ſame accompt, ſo that now I muſt proceed in a rational order and method whereby to convince your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and underſtandings in this caſe, or elſe all that I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto laboured in, will turn to no Accompt, as to my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent deſign. Wherefore in anſwer thereunto I will lay down this poſition for a general maxime (for you will find it uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally true) <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That all Cities, Corporations, Bodies politick, Market-Towns and the like, have all of them (more or leſs) their publique Places, and Publick-Houſes built (ſuch as Halls) Courts of Judicature, Market Houſes, Store-houſes, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171654:18"/>and the like) for the Honour, State, Benefit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, Profit, Advantage and Accommodation of the ſame, and all theſe publick places built upon the publick charges, have as certain (and though to outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſomewhat inſenſible) and conſtant revenue and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance (eſpecially in great Cities) belonging unto them in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their defraying the ſaid publick and neceſſary charges, as any Landlord whatſoever, that hath laid out 500 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> in Building of an houſe and thereupon doth receive ſome 30 40 or 50 <hi>pounds per annum</hi> as a yearly rent for the ſame.</p>
            <p>This being premiſed, I ſhall now bring it to the matter in hand, by a particular inſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> That this famous and moſt Magnificent ſtructure of the Royal Exchange, is one of the moſt neceſſary and moſt publick places that is built within your Metrapolitane City of <hi>London,</hi> although there are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others, as <hi>Guild-Hall, The Chamber of London, The Court of Aldermen, your Market-Houſes, your Store-houſes, your Courts of Judicature, the two Counters, your Priſon for Felons,</hi> and the like which are of the ſame import, and pray where is your viſible and apparent revenue (whereby to re-imburſe you) that you do receive for them? and yet notwithſtanding you have ſo ordered the matter as that all theſe places (and that not without very good reaſon, as being eſſentially ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and requiſite as to the flouriſhing Eſtate of your City for the future) are already built. And that you ſhall be as certainly and as ſurely reimburſed, and that with a moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable advantage for all your coſt and charges ſo expended; I ſhall make it clearly appear in manner and form as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That it is as requiſite and neceſſary (but more eſpecially in ſo famous and ſo renowned a City as the City of <hi>London</hi>) that all ſuch publick places ſhould be built, and kept con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly in repair at the publick charges, in expectation of the future benefit and advantage which the whole body ſhould receive thereby, as it is requiſite and neceſſary, that a Shop
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171654:18"/>keeper ſhould lay out 500 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> in ſtaple commodities, whereby to furniſh his ſhop in expectation of a future trade, or for a Merchant to freight out a ſhip to Sea with the Manufactures of <hi>England,</hi> upon his own accompt, in expectation to receive a conſiderable advantage thereby, at his ſafe, ſpeedy, and happy return. And now whereas you have built this place for the honour of His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> ſo you have likewiſe made it more eſpecially, and in particular, for the accommodation of the Merchants, and all others who have converſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and traffick with them, for the advance of your Trade, for the enriching of your members, and ſtill as they do thrive, floriſh &amp; grow rich, it is ten to one but you do find them out, and call upon them for Aldermen, and for Sheriffs, and where one holds there is many goes off by the way of fines; and here is that ſecret miſtery and inſenſible revenue before intimated, brought to light (beſides many other wayes and means you have to bring yearly great Sums into your Publick Treaſury) &amp; although you do not, nor ſhould not receive ſo much quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, by the way of Rent, yet you do conſtantly and ſurely receive as much, if not more than the intereſt of your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys ſo laid out, by the way of Fines. And pray what are all theſe Fines leavyed upon the Inhabitants and rich mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of your City (and in other Corporations and Bodies Politick) but to defray all the Publick and neceſſary char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, upon this very accompt; and this will ſtill hold and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, ſo long as your City remains and continues in the like good and flouriſhing condition, which the Lord of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercy grant may be until time ſhall be no more, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come now let us reaſon together (pray pardon this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar though modeſt expreſſion, in regard I muſt confeſs I have that high value and reſpect for that which we call Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that I am unwilling to move forward one ſtep farther in any concern whatſoever, than I am guided and directed by the light thereof) I will now take it for granted, that upon the precedent conſiderations, you would have rebuilt the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171654:19"/>
               <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> if you had not had one Tenant to have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited within the walls thereof. And if ſo, I would only beg the favour to ask you theſe queſtions, <hi>Viz.</hi> would you not have built it with Pillars? would you not have covered it with Lead? would you not have paved it with Marble? would you not have built it with ſtone? would you not have erected their Majeſties Effigies in the front, as alſo the Effigies of the firſt Founder? would you not have made ſuch a ſtately Tower as is now Erected? and the like; and theſe are the things which make ſuch a noiſe in your build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in the report of the people, and which do ariſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo vaſt a Sum in your books of Accompt. Now I ſay, put all theſe things (here mentioned) together, and calculate the charge thereof as near as poſſibly you can, &amp; charge all theſe unto the Publick Accompt, and when this is done, then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the remaining charge which you have built for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation of ſhop-keepers within the ſaid place, and then leavy their proportions to re-imburſe you for the intereſt of your money ſo laid out, and for the principal alſo in due time.</p>
            <p>And now as to thoſe walls of Brick, wherein your Tenants are incloſed by ſome mens computation (I muſt acknowledge my ſelf no competent Judge therein; as being neither Brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layer, Stone-cutter, Maſon, nor Carpenter) with all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident charges appertaining thereunto, and which you have made for the accomodation of your ſaid Tenants, could not coſt you above 10000 pounds; and as theſe ſtately and magnificent adjuncts before-mentioned, and wherewith your Tenants are environed and ſurrounded, is no part of the building, at leaſt no part thereof ſo far as to be charged to the Inhabitants accompts, but to the account currant, <hi>viz.</hi> the Publick Account.</p>
            <p>And here by the way, had one hundred of the preſent inhabitants, during the time they were in <hi>Greſham Colledge,</hi> but made application to Alderman <hi>Backwell,</hi> and have taken
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171654:19"/>that piece of ground juſt before your <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they had given 500 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum</hi> only for the ground Rent, which would have been 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> a piece, and after that had laid down fifty pounds a piece, to be laid out in building, which would have amounted to 5000 pounds, what a ſtate<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly place might they have built therewith the ſaid money for their own accommodations; I will aſſure you far beyond the Accommodation they have at preſent within your Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, and you have charged the place with at leaſt 50000 pounds, for the inhabitants to work out, and to pay you the Intereſt of your money. And you have not reſted here neither, (I do not ſpeak here to any of you perſonally, and in particular, but only as you are now aſſembled in Court) but it is ſaid that you have made your Tenants pay by way of overplus, for their Windows, for their Stalls, and for the backs and footpaces of your ſaid Shops; and whoever heard, that houſes and ſhops were ever let by Leaſe or yearly Rent, without the eſſential properties and neceſſary adjuncts and qualifications of Doors and Windows, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto appertaining and belonging; but they were not put upon any ſuch ſtratagem, by reaſon that they did build and rely ſo much upon your Clemency, Moderation and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence towards them.</p>
            <p>But I hope theſe precedent arguments before mentioned, as to this inſenſible Revenue, and as to the flouriſhing eſtate of your <hi>Royal City,</hi> will for the future take ſome impreſſion upon all the hearts of this honourable Court, whereby they may anſwer the deſires and expectations of all their immediat Tenants (who are concerned herein) to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.</p>
            <p>And now as to the flouriſhing and thriving eſtate of your Metropolitan City, I may very well compare it unto a large, pleaſant and fertile Park (and for methods and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations ſake, we will call it the Park of <hi>Englands</hi> Nonſuch) out of which, in ſeven years time, is rouzed out of the brakes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171654:20"/>and hunted out of the woodsthereof, many an overgrown Deer into the Chamber of <hi>London,</hi> and when he comes there, if he bleeds freely, before the Lord keepers of the ſaid Park (either in ſpring or fall, or about or near the time the Sun enters the Equinoctial) it is a very great ſign that he is fat within, and of a ſanguine and healthful Conſtitution, and the ſeveral ounces there taken from him, are preſerved in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick ſtore, not only as a worthy relique, to preſerve his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture remembrance, but alſo of ſoveraign uſe and benefit, to be expended upon all occaſions (here is your publique reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue and publick charges within a very ſmall compaſs, very happily and opportunely met and joyned together; and by my conſent they ſhould never again be parted or divorced, but for ſome extraordinary and ſpecial occaſion given for the ſame) towards the continual repair and keeping up of the incloſures, the Pales and the Walls of the ſaid Park, in order to the greater ſecurity and preſervation, for the future, of the reſt of the Herd.</p>
            <p>But if this will not do, and if you are ſtill reſolved to charge upon your Tenants the whole ſtreſs and weight of the building (which I am afraid is ſo heavy as that they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able long to ſupport themſelves under it) then I will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to make one ſtep farther with you, (whereby to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leviate the preſent charge of your ſaid Tenants) and that is, by an humble propoſal unto this honourable Court, <hi>viz.</hi> That you would be pleaſed to procure an act of Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel (which your ſeveral Charters and Priviledges for your Liberties, for all neceſſary charges will bear you out in) whereby to levy 20 or 40 <abbr>s.</abbr> 
               <hi>per annum</hi> (which will be but a very inconſiderable charge unto them, though in the whole will amount unto a very conſiderable ſumme) upon every eminent Merchant and Broker (who do daily frequent your <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> and there deal for thouſands and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in a week, and pay nothing for their Station) rather than levy the whole charge upon the preſent (and God knows
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171654:20"/>many of them very poor) inhabitants. But if in caſe an act of Common Councel will not reach them, then to be ſure an Act of Parliament will do it (and that effectually) to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>But you will now object and ſay, (eſpecially on the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies ſide) That according to theſe maxims, reaſons and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations the City of <hi>London,</hi> receives more benefit and advantage by far, as to this inſenſible revenue here diſcuſſed and deſcribed, by the rebuilding of the City of <hi>London</hi> and in particular the Royal Exchange within the ſaid place, and by the conſtant, flouriſhing and thriving eſtate thereof, then the Mercers do, and yet they are both equally concerned as to the charge of the rebuilding thereof.</p>
            <p>In anſwer hereunto I muſt acknowledge (and ingeniouſly confeſs) the truth hereof in the affirmative, and the truth of it is, by all the Rhetorick in my budget and by all the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and reaſons that I can rally up, and muſter together, I am not able to ſolve this objection, with ſatisfaction to any rational man whatſoever. Wherefore if the City and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany would agree (and it is great pity that ſuch an Antient Society, and ſuch co-partners who have lived ſo long toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Amity and Unity ſhould now fall out) to put it to the Vote, in the next Common-Hall holden for the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> they ſhould have both my hands (as an unworthy mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereof) that the City ſhould contribute two thirds, and the Right Worſhipful Company of Mercers one third to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the charge of the Building, and when this is done, that they ſhould both (as co-partners ſtill) be equally concerned as to the rents, incomes, revenues, and profits of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And here by the way although neither of you do receive a proportionable revenue and income in your way and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod (and by the meaſures as you have taken for the ſame) according to your primary expectations, yet behold here is Honour, Credit and reputation enough in the caſe to ſupply that defect, for now ſince the rebuilding of your moſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171654:21"/>ſtately and moſt Magnificent ſtructure (for as to the whole theſe are proper and deſerving Epithites, and as to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation for Traders, I could wiſh it were ſo in every part and parcel thereof) you my Lord Mayor the repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Body of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and you the worthy mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this grand Committee, the repreſentative Body of the right Worſhipful Company of Mercers, are now eſteemed and reputed as famous for your zeal &amp; care and for your expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in order to the accompliſhment of the ſaid building, as the worthy Sir <hi>Thomas Greſham</hi> was formerly (and ever will be as long as your City ſtands) who was the firſt Founder thereof; and truly this is a very great honour indeed, for how many perſons hath there been in the World, who have done many Worthy and moſt Noble acts in order to perpetuate their names unto poſterity, and to leave a good example be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, that others might be induced and encouraged to follow and tread in their ſteps, and as I have been inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a very worthy Perſon of this Nation, who did formerly proffer (which would have coſt him many thouſand pounds) to finiſh upon his own coſt and charges, the Quadrangle of <hi>Christ Church Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> upon condition that he might be made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but Co-founder, which it ſeems was ſuch an high punctillio of Honour, Credit and Reputation eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Heads of the ſaid <hi>Colledge</hi> (and of which they were ſo tender and careful) as that they would by no meanes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thereof, inaſmuch as by ſuch an act and by ſuch an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollment upon record, would mount him upon the Wings of Everlaſting fame unto poſterity, to be coequal with Cardinal <hi>Woolſey</hi> who was the firſt Founder thereof.</p>
            <p>And now if ſome Worthy and Wealthy Perſon (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome rich Batchelor of the City of <hi>London</hi>) would lay out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> much money as to make thoſe alterations in the Royal Exchange (and the charges would not amount unto a very great ſumme) in the ſame manner and form as is before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ribed, I am very certainly aſſured he would be eſteemed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171654:21"/>and reputed as famous and as worthy unto Poſterity among all perſons that ſhould ſee the ſame, but more eſpecially among the Merchants of <hi>London,</hi> and the Inhabitants that ſhould hereafter ſurvive and flouriſh therein, as any publick ſpirited Perſon hath been formerly upon any Account what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. And here I will not divine, but I have a ſtrong perſwaſion within my Breaſt, that ſome worthy Perſon or other will pleaſe (either ſooner or later) to take the Premiſes into his private and moſt ſerious conſideration: But if not, I ſay ſtill for the City of <hi>London</hi> (like a ſtrong Noun Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive, ſuch as <hi>Rex</hi> or <hi>Regnum,</hi> which ſtandeth by it ſelf) to lay out twenty or thirty thouſand pounds, as a ſtrong, ſolid and ſubſtantial Foundation, in order for an Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for the future thriving and flouriſhing Eſtate and Condition of their ſaid City, which after muſt be laid for the Superſtructure and Top-ſtone of ſuch a Noble and Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Building, is no more with them, than for ſome of their <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> Tenants, when they have ſold a rich poynt of <hi>Venice</hi> to ſome perſons of quality, of a hundred pound price, and after that to give a little Paper and Pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thread to bind it up into their bargain.</p>
            <p>So that now ſhould you at length by rational means be perſwaded (which is not as yet too late) to make upon your own Coſt and Charges (without ſtanding in competition with any other moſt worthy Perſon) ſuch convenient Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations as are here mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To build out the four Corners of your <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> (which now ſtandeth in Nooks) that ſo there may be a perfect Quadrangle both below and above ſtairs within the ſaid place, which ſaid Alterations will be altogether as gracefull to the two Fronts as they are now: But if a Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould endeavour to perſwade you to the contrary, (although perhaps he could give but a ſlender Reaſon for the ſame) yet one would think in reaſon that Gracefulneſs in this place ſhould not come in competition with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171654:22"/>of a Trade: And I dare ſwear, that theſe Grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full works, not of Uniformity but Deformity, hath ſo mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Intereſt of your Outward Pawns above ſtairs, as to an Equality of Rents, ſo as that you had better have given two or three thouſand Pounds out of your Publick Stock, than to have permitted them to be built after the ſame manner as they are at this day.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To take down the Middle walls above ſtairs, and not the Roof (which peradventure you would think too great a charge) and build it upon Pillars, with deep Shops on both ſides, as formerly deſcribed, and alſo to take down the walls below ſtairs, and there erect Pillars in lieu there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with Shops onely of one ſide, as before mentioned, where the Bricks you take down, would go near to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervail your ſaid Charge; which being done, would bring you in a moſt certain Revenue of at leaſt 4000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum,</hi> and every perſon alſo contented and well ſatisfied, and would think himſelf alſo moſt reaſonably uſed. And if you ſhould object, That you could not afford the Place at ſuch a Rent, (and will have no reſpect, nor give any grains of Allowance unto the precedent Arguments) the next ſeven years Leaſes, if Trading ſhould flow in upon them, they would as willingly then (when they are all ſettled and eſtabliſhed in the ſaid place) pay you 6000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum,</hi> as they will now pay you Four.</p>
            <p>And upon ſuch Alterations it will be objected, that the preſent ſtairs of the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> will be ſuch a break in the Quadrangle below ſtairs, as will much impair the Gracefulneſs of the ſaid place: Unto the which I anſwer, I have a very convenient and commodious Salvo for that alſo; but that is too tender a part at preſent to be here diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed, by reaſon there muſt be a particular Demonſtration upon the very place, to ſatisfie any rational man of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience thereof.</p>
            <p>But if no Alterations in the leaſt Meaſure ſhould enſue
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171654:22"/>hereupon, then as to the <hi>quantum merun</hi> or your preſent Shops, as to matter of Rents: I anſwer in Manner and Form as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That in conſideration of the many preceding Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, and the many unavoidable Circumſtances that do and will alwayes attend the ſaid place. Your Shops <hi>re vera &amp; bona fide,</hi> cannot poſſibly be valued (eſpecially were an honeſt Jury upon their Oaths to give in their Verdict in the Caſe) at more than 10 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum,</hi> and whoever hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly given, or ſhall hereafter give more, I will not ſay, it is not for want of Ignorance, (for that would be a little too groſs) but I will ſay, it is either out of Inadvertency, as not conſidering what they undertake, or elſe out of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, as being bred up as Apprentices in your <hi>Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> and know not (poor Souls) how to provide for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves elſewhere for a future livelihood.</p>
            <p>And now as to this inſenſible (and not ſo much perceived and taken notice of) Revenue for your diſcharge of all theſe publick places, and doth ſo much depend upon the future thriving and flouriſhing Condition of your Metropolitan City; I ſay in anſwer thereunto, I will ſtill ſtand my ground, and will not move one ſtep from the point in hand by way of Retreat, (unleſs I am overcome by might, or rather by better Arguments to the contrary) but will ſtill hold it out as a ſtrong City of Refuge, and as an advantageous Poſt, or a ſtrong Tower of Defence, againſt all oppoſition what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. And now in the cloſe of all, and to wind it up in a ſmall bottom, I will make ſuch a clear demonſtration thereof unto you all, by two moſt famous Inſtances and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes, taken from thoſe two grand Luminaries of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and which are there fixed by the God of Nature, (the Supream and Superintendent Being of all created Beings whatſoever) for the uſe, benefit, ſervice and advantage of his little <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his Creature Man; the one to rule the Day, and the other to govern the Night:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171654:23"/>And firſt for the Sun, this vaſt fiery and Elementary Body, this all-glorious Lamp of Heaven (which as the Scripture phraſes it, <hi>cometh forth of his Chamber like a Bridegroom, and rejoyceth as a ſtrong Man to run his race,</hi>) which conſiſteth in Light, Life, Heat and Motion, and by its moſt wonderful ſecret Power, and inſenſible Faculties, it doth produce the ſame moſt admirable Effects, unto all Creatures both Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal and Inanimal whatſoever, upon the face of the whole Earth; and the nearer and nearer it doth approach unto us, (within our Horizon) the more vigour, ſtrength and power it doth ſtill retain, in order to the accompliſhment of all thoſe Noble Ends and Purpoſes for the which it was firſt created, and by reaſon of his powerfull Influence over the whole Earth, he doth never reſt Day nor Night, untill ſuch time as he hath enriched the ſame with a plentifull Crop, and all things therein contained with a Green, thriving and flouriſhing Condition; ſo that from hence (by the wiſe Diſpoſer of all things under the Sun) we have the Spring and the Fall, we have Summer and Winter, Seed-time and Harveſt, and all things that may conduce unto our preſent and future Happineſs whatſoever: And this is a true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation and Similitude of Life and Death, as to things Temporal, Mortality, Reſurrection, and Immortality, as to things Spiritual and Eternal: And ſo in like manner, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the other moſt glorious and Nocturnal Light, this vaſt, Elementary, moiſt and liquid Body of the Moon (which as Aſtrologers do ſay, is above three hundred times bigger than the whole Terreſtrial Univerſe) and hath ſo powerfull an Influence upon the vaſt Ocean, ſo that as we ſee by daily Experience, as ſhe increaſes in Grandeur, <hi>Neptune</hi> himſelf is alſo conſtrained to move forward, and to give way, and to increaſe alſo, and ſo gradually till ſhe comes to her full ſtrength, then the Surges and Billowes of the Sea do ariſe to that height, as many times it overflowes the banks of the main Ocean, and this is that which we call our Spring-tides.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171654:23"/>So that we ſee this vaſt and liquid Body (like as Fire doth produce Fire, and Water by the help of an Engine doth draw up Water) by its ſecret and attractive virtue (infuſed thereinto by an Almighty power) commands the very Ocean it ſelf, and likewiſe ſets bounds and limits to the proud waves and ſurges thereof, (which many times are much higher than the Land) by its moſt powerfull ſtrength, influence and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>And this is a more than probable Argument to be given for the Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea, which hath ſtartled and ſtumbled ſo many Perſons, who have been upon the Queſt to find out the true Cauſe and Reaſon thereof. And theſe two Inſtances alone, together with the Rainbow being taken in, which will make up a Trinity of Celeſtial Atteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, are enough to confute (thoſe purblind and blear-ey'd Maſters of Reaſon, who can ſee no further than their dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted corporeal Eyes will permit them) the proudeſt and ſtouteſt Atheiſt in the world.</p>
            <p>And they may as well ſay, that they made themſelves, and were the primary Cauſe of their own Beings, as to ſay, all theſe things and many more (which would bee too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious here to inſert) were firſt produced by the power, ſtrength and vigour onely of Natures Operation: For how can theſe men tell, that if Nature alone did produce them, Nature might not ſome time or other reduce them again un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their firſt Principles, or elſe into ſome other Form and Faſhion? (for Nature ſometimes hath its prodigious and monſtrous Births;) And how could they tell that the Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow (Gods eſtabliſhed Covenant with Mankind) ſhould continue and appear in the Heavens for ſo many Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? But all theſe things are ſo fixed and determined by the moſt High, that they cannot do otherwiſe than they are appointed, and if the Sun ſtand ſtill or go backwards at any time, it is in Obedience to the Command of the Supreme Creator.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:171654:24"/>
            <p>I pray pardon this ſmall digreſſion of mine, in regard as I was entring thereupon ſome of the Atheiſtical notions did ſo boldly accoſt me, that I could do no leſs then give them a broad ſide, on purpoſe to ſend them back again into the Land of forgetfulneſs; that ſo they might no more riſe up in pride, vain-glory, and preſumption in denying the good Providence and Wiſdom of Almighty God in theſe and the like caſes, but to proceed as by way of ſimilitude in theſe two inſtances, as to thoſe ends and purpoſes now mentioned, ſo I ſay in like manner, as to this moſt Famous and moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned City of <hi>London,</hi> ſo long as you have peace within your Walls, Proſperity within your Borders, Plenty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Streets, Health within your Pallaces; no Forreign nor Domeſtique jarrs to obſtruct your Trade at home, nor your Negotiations abroad (eſpecially among your Merchants which are the great wheeles or ſprings in a Watch that ſets all the little wheels in their orderly motions) Mercy and Truth meeting together, Righteouſneſs and Peace embracing each other, I ſay by the powerful influence of all theſe precedent circumſtances being met and joyned together, it is almoſt impoſſible but that your City of <hi>London,</hi> (unleſs our heaven provoking ſins from time to time interveneing ſhall forbid the banes) ſhould continue in a thriving and flouriſhing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and thereupon how many thouſand pounds come flowing yearly (like the overflowing of the River <hi>Nilus</hi>) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Chamber of <hi>London,</hi> and at this inſenſible vaſt and moſt Noble revenue, the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> and the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof are not in the leaſt meaſure offended, but do ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rejoyce and wiſh you much joy thereof, and much good may you do with it, and they would be glad with all their hearts every Mothers child of them, to arrive at the ſame pitch of honour as to come to be Lord Major, Mr. Alderman, Mr. Sheriff, Mr. Common-Councel-Man and the like. And now and then to open a vein in the body Politick, for the preſervation of the whole is as requiſite and neceſſary as ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171654:24"/>to open a vein in the body natural, whereby to remove ſome impediment and obſtruction in the circulation of the blood, that ſo afterwards in its perambulation it may run with more ſtrength and vigor, and return again unto its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and regular proceedings. And I may truly ſay of this antient and Renowned City of <hi>London</hi> (and it reaches all caſes, perſons and places whatſoever) according to the Poet.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Donec eris foelix multos numerabis amicos,</l>
               <l>Tempora ſi fuerint nubila ſolus eris.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ovid</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>And thus have I done with my main and principal deſign which were my primary intentions and reſolutions in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blication hereof.</p>
            <p>And although this ſmall piece is not adorned with all thoſe goodly and excellent properties as might be expected from a perſon of more than ordinary and Scholaſtick improvement, upon any matter or Subject whatſoever as he ſhould under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take which are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To ſpeak modeſtly, and in the words of truth and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety.</item>
               <item>2. To ſpeak pertinent to the matter in hand (without too many circumlocutions and florid expreſſions before he comes to the point) and therein alſo to be very ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct.</item>
               <item>3. To back all his poſitions, and aſſertions with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing and powerfull arguments of ſolid and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial reaſon, that ſo all perſons may be conſtrained to acquieſce in her determinations, as not being able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the ſtrength and power thereof.</item>
            </list>
            <p>As to the firſt of theſe I am conſcious to my ſelf that I have not ſwerved therefrom, and as for the two latter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I have been ſhort, you muſt impute it to my mean educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſlender abilities and not to my well wiſhes in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the ſame, and yet herein I have endeavoured as
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171654:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>much as in me lyes, &amp; as the matter would bear, to make them as ſuccinct as I could, and I am ſure I have repreſented things ſo plain, ſo obvious and profpicuous (and upon the ſquare) to any intelligent perſon, ſo as that he that runs may read: If at leaſt he dare but make uſe of his reaſon, in theſe Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and humane affairs, as well as thoſe moſt Heroick, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal and Publick ſpirited men of this age (to their Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing praiſe, Honour and perpetual remembrance and Renown be it ſpoken) have done (although by ſome perſons they are alſo (the more is the pity) moſt bitterly inveighed and railed againſt for their ſo doing) in matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>And were it not beſides the matter in hand (and likewiſe more proper to another function than my own,) I could here willingly give theſe Gentlemen of the black and ruſſet guard, half a dozen good ſmart blowes (which ſhould ſtick cloſe to their ſides) for their Satyrical invectives and railings, both in Preſs and Pulpit; againſt theſe moſt Noble and Chriſtian like <hi>Beroeans</hi> who have univerſal Love, Charity and good will for all perſons and of all perſwaſions whatſoever (I am afraid they do much fall ſhort, of this antient Catholick and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Temper,) and who do ſee more with one of their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (having the eyes of their underſtandings thereby enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) than ten thouſand of them, who, although they have <hi>(ſicut homines)</hi> their diſcerning and intellectual faculties (and both their Ocular ſences as to their corporeal parts) yet do at this day ſo much ſtumble (in Charity I muſt, and am obliged to pity them notwithſtanding) and grope in the dark.</p>
            <p>But I hope when this thick vail of ignorance (more than <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigypan</hi> darkneſs) is taken off from the minds and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of men (by theſe Worthy perſons even now hinted, and which are in preſent Communion with the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) and that they may once be brought to that paſs, as to ſee with their own and not other mens eyes, then thoſe wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Clouds of error, ſuperſtition and Idolatry, and all thoſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171654:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>aiery notions and moſt ſtrange, horrid and irrational ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, whoſe natural tendency is more to make men vitious than vertuous, and which have ſo long peſtered the true Church, and (which to enumerate would make a large volumn of it ſelf) will by degrees evaporate, and like miſts and foggs before the riſing Sun will in a ſhort time vaniſh and fall to the ground: and that it may be in ſome good meaſure accompliſhed in our dayes, let all Sober and Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Chriſtians (who are enjoyned at all times to ſtand upon their guard, and to be ready to give a reaſon of their Faith, and of that good hope that is in them with meekneſs and fear) to inſert this into their Litany and daily prayers, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Exurgat Deus et veritatis diſsipentur inimici.</q>
            <p>And now, what will become of this ſmall peice, and how this innocent Dove will be treated now it is out my hands, (I having no ſuch proſpect in my thoughts, nor yet in the leaſt meaſure pretending thereunto) I am not able here to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, although I preſume this I may ſafely ſay <hi>(ſecundum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis rationem)</hi> that it will meet with many a bluſtring ſtorm and cruel Tempeſts before it finds any reſt or harbour for the ſole of its foot, and before it return again (by a fair brisk and proſperous gale) with an Olive branch in its mouth.</p>
            <p>But this one thing I can certainly aſſure you, (and I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it is an auſpicious <hi>Omen,</hi> and I hope it doth amount almoſt unto a ſure and certain preſage) <hi>viz.</hi> That although your preſent Authour, is a perſon naturally of very mean and ſlender abilities, (and not ſet of with theſe blandiſhments and grand auxilliaries, and Artificial helps of Scholaſtick en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments and accompliſhments, which do uſually raiſe men to ſomething in the world) and thereupon altogether unable to expoſe himſelf to publick view, wherein he muſt undergo the various cenſures of all Critical perſons whatſoever: Yet when theſe preſent notions did firſt enter, and caſt Anchor within his private cogitations, and afterwards having ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:171654:26"/>and ſoberly weighed, examined, pondered and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered all circumſtances whatſoever relating thereunto, and caſting up the ſumme total, he found upon the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, That they being of ſuch univerſal benefit and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, (if they were once put in Execution) and of ſuch publick tendency, as well for the Honour of the King, for the Honour of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> the Honour of your Royal City, (as being the chief Reſidence of Sacred Majeſty) as alſo for the Relief of thoſe many honeſt and good Perſons, who are at preſent under great Preſſures, and are not able to extricate themſelves out of the ſame, but by the interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of your Power and Authority, and of your Clemency and Indulgence towards them: I ſay, for theſe and the like conſiderations, he found ſuch a Conſternation in his mind, ſuch a confuſion in his thoughts, ſuch a perplexity within his breaſt, as that he could not receive any real ſatisfaction or quiet within himſelf, untill he had put his hand to the Plough, <hi>viz.</hi> his Pen to paper, whereby to bring them into ſuch a decent and orderly Method, fitting to be publiſhed and preſented unto this Honourable Court: And when I ſaid for the Honour of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> methinks I find ſuch an Emphaſis in the words, as that I am not able to paſs any further without making an Halt, or ſome ſmall Retreat, (and that by way of Paraphraſe upon the words,) whereby to leave unto Poſterity, <hi>viz.</hi> to the Inhabitants of this Iſland, (but more eſpecially to all thoſe who ſhall have the peruſal hereof) ſomething of Remembrance, whereby to excite them all unto a moſt real, and a moſt unfeigned Gratitude and Thankfulneſs unto the Supreme Monarch of Heaven and Earth, that their Lots are fallen in ſo good an Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as to be born within the Limits, Confines, Territories and Dominions thereof.</p>
            <p>For as to this Iſland of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> (this ſure I am) I may ſafely and truely ſay, That it may properly be called <hi>The Phoenix of the World,</hi> upon theſe and the like ſubſequent Conſiderations, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:171654:26"/>
            <p n="1">1. For the Conſtitution of its Government, (pray ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, this is the Foundation-ſtone) for the Scituation of the Place, for Conveniency of Trade, and for the Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties therein produced, for the Encouragement of all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants for Exportation and Importation, for its ſtrength a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Forreign Invaſions, as being environed with the Sea like the City of <hi>Venice,</hi> whoſe Motto is,
<q>
                  <l>Thus free from all Alarms,</l>
                  <l>I reſt in Neptunes Arms.</l>
               </q> (Many Princes and People, who live upon the main Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, how glad would they be of ſuch an Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who are in perpetual Fear and Jeopardy every day, by incurſions from their Neighbours;) As alſo for the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Climate, for the Valour of its Subjects, for the Diſpoſition of the People, <hi>Cum multis aliis quae nunc,</hi> &amp;c. and (which is the Top-ſtone of this moſt ſtately Structure,) for the moſt pure, and moſt ſpiritual Worſhip of God, that is here exhibited and enjoyed, of any Nation at this day under the Sun. And when I ſaid, for the Conſtitution of its Government, there is again ſuch an Emphaſis in thoſe words, that I muſt make a double Retreat, <hi>viz.</hi> under a Mild and Gentle, and not a Tyrannical Prince: Whereas in many other Countreys, their Monarchs do ſay, <q>Sic volo, ſic jubeo, ſtat pro ratione voluntas, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> But bleſſed be God, in this Iſland we are not in the ſame Condition, but we can ſay, according to that generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and known Maxim in the Law, Our Gracious King by the Conſtitution of the Government it ſelf <hi>can doe no Wrong,</hi> (it being beneath the State and Majeſty of a Prince to execute any of his Laws in his own Perſon) but if any wrong be done, in matters of State, the Councel, and if in Matters of Law, the Judges, the ſubordinate Magiſtrates, the Juſtices, and all other inferiour Officers, (whoſe Power
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:171654:27"/>is onely derivative from this Fountain,) are to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for Male-adminiſtration, and by this ancient and moſt famous Triple League of King, Lords and Commons (God grant that it may never be broken nor diſſolved) this Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of words, and their Trinity in Unity, and Unity in Trinity (which with Reverence be it ſpoken) is a fair Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation and Illuſtration of the Trinity and Unity of the three ſacred Perſons in the higheſt Heavens: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they are not one in Nature and Eſſence (as is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged and acknowledged by ſome, and is alſo an Article of their Faith, as to thoſe three Divine Perſons,) which is altogether impoſſible, as having their diſtinct Beings, their diſtinct Offices, their diſtinct Names, and although in ſo near a Conjunction, conſiſt of many diſtinct Perſons; yet they are one in mutual Conſent and Agreement, (and here the <hi>Socinians</hi> will tell you, that three diſtinct Perſons, either Divine, Angelical, or Humane, to be made one in Nature and Eſſence, is altogether impoſſible, and will never be made out to any rational Man while the world ſtands;) and for any Perſon to inferr from hence, that becauſe they are one in mutual Conſent and Agreement, therefore they are co-ordinate in Power and Authority, I preſume is a very great Miſtake, and to ſay, that the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty is, <hi>Major ſingulis, ſed Minor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis,</hi> is an Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſame validity and import; for then it would unavoidably follow, that we have at this day in our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on three Supreams; whereas in Reaſon there cannot poſſible be (unleſs we ſhould root out, eradicate and ſubvert the common and in-bred Notion of Mankind,) but one Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream. But ſuppoſe it had ſome colour of Truth in it, (which we will admit for Arguments ſake) that they are co-ordinate in Power by virtue of this Unity, yet it is onely in the Legiſlative Power; and here alſo for matter of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and councel onely, for they are called the great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of the Nation, and they are ſummoned by the Kings
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:171654:27"/>Writ, and do ſit, not as long as they pleaſe, but <hi>durante Regis beneplacito;</hi> and for the Executive power, all the Laws of <hi>England</hi> run in his Majeſties Name, and a breach of them are deemed and reputed a breach of his Majeſties Laws: And although you may ſay alſo concerning his Vice-royes, Ambaſſadours, and Deputy-Lievtenants, that in ſome ſence they are co-ordinate in Power (by reaſon they do many things in as uncontrollable a manner, as if the King himſelf were perſonally preſent,) and an affront offered to them, is an affront offered to the King himſelf, for it terminates in him, inaſmuch as they do repreſent the Kings Perſon and Authority: But ſince theſe rational Demonſtrations bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der too much upon the <hi>Socinian</hi> Tenents (which in this and other precedent Ages have been by moſt men eſteemed and reputed heterodox) I muſt forbear. But yet this I ſay, by vertue of this Trinity in Unity, and Unity in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <hi>viz.</hi> this mutual Oneneſs and Agreement in Conſent one with another, this Conſtitution and Foundation hath continued ſtedfaſt and immoveable for ſo many hundred years, (ſave onely of late years, by a moſt ſtrange and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of Cataſtrophe, and by a moſt diſmal and prodigious Interval;) and God grant that it may ſtill continue to run in the ſame Channel, rather than in a worſe, untill <hi>Shiloh</hi> come, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now my ever Honoured, moſt Noble, and my much eſteemed good Lord, and you the worthy Knights, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Citizens, Members of this Grand Committee, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this new-born and tender Infant (for ſome Reaſons inducing me thereunto) comes to wait on you, in this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and unexpected Dreſs, <hi>viz. incognito,</hi> and thereupon not attended with that formal and accuſtomed Ceremony, (too often uſed in this and the like Caſes, the more is the pity) of Eſpouſing parties to ſecond his honeſt and plain-hearted deſign, yet if this tender Babe (by all the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Arguments herein contained) be not able to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:171654:28"/>ſpeak for it ſelf, and to plead its own Cauſe, then let all the Concerns thereof, henceforward and for ever fall to the ground; but if it ſhall ſo far prevail, as to contribute any thing towards the Relief of thoſe Perſons for whom it was firſt deſigned, (and of whom you have here a particular Catalogue,) I have my deſire. For, as according to our common and proverbial ſaying, viz. <hi>We are not all born to be Rich,</hi> ſo on the other hand, which is of a far more ſaving and univerſal tendency, <hi>Non nobis ſolum nati ſumus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And inaſmuch as I can expect no Conſideration or Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity from any particular Man, or from any number or So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of men, for my pains in Writing, or Expence in Printing this preſent Addreſs to you of this Honourable Court, ſo ſhall I be willing to reſt ſatisfied and contented in this, <hi>viz.</hi> That it was for a general and publick Good; and therefore I ſhall place it (as you ought, <hi>de jure,</hi> in my ſlender apprehenſions, according to the precedent Reaſons, but with a Reſerve alwayes to your more accurate and diſcerning Judgements, the Charge of your <hi>Royal Exchange</hi>) <hi>viz.</hi> to the publick Accompt, and that in ſure and certain hopes alſo (for I will ſtill run parallel with you) that in proceſs of time, it may pay both Principal and Intereſt, (only yours is certain, and mine uncertain, but <hi>dum ſpiro ſpero,</hi>) and in the Concluſion may with an Over-plus turn ſomething of Advantage unto your Authors accompt.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, if it do not at preſent anſwer the Expectations and Deſires of thoſe poor Perſons, who doe ſtill wait, and expect with patience ſome Relief from your Clemency and Indulgence, yet notwithſtanding I ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes heartily pray for the continual peace, Proſperity, and flouriſhing Eſtate of your Metropolitan City, and in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular for all your Tenants and preſent Inhabitants (many whereof are my worthy Friends and Acquaintance) of your <hi>Royal Exchange;</hi> but I will aſſure you, (if you will pleaſe to pardon my preſent preſumption, in ſo much tiring your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:171654:28"/>in peruſal of this Memorial) I ſhall never trouble you nor my ſelf, nor any ſucceding Committee, upon this or the like Account. So committing you all to the conſtant and continual Care, Conduct and Protection of the moſt High, wiſhing that all your Debates and Conſultations hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, may be agreeable and conſonant unto that which is a Spark and Ray of that Divine Beauty and Luſtre, who is the Sourſe and Fountain of all Rectitude and Perfection, <hi>viz.</hi> Reaſon, and that all your future Proceedings and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, here in this lower and Terreſtrial Sphear, may be according to the orderly, conſtant, and regular Motions of the Coeleſtial Bodies in the Superiour Orb: And that all your Edicts henceforward may be (like the Laws and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of Heaven it ſelf, to all the Sons and Daughters of Men,) of moſt ſovereign and ſaving Uſe, and of univerſal Benefit and Advantage, unto all thoſe who ſhall or may be concerned in them, but more eſpecially and in particular at this preſent conjuncture, unto all the preſent Inhabitants (<hi>&amp; de futuro,</hi> for all thoſe who ſhall there actually ſucceed,) within the walls of your <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> (for theſe, and theſe onely are the Men, which muſt repair, ſuſtain, uphold, defend and keep up the future Credit, Reputation and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the ſaid place.)</p>
            <p>And now to conclude all in a ſhort Parable, (for Parables many times, and in ſome Caſes, have taken as deep an Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if not more, than a plainer Demonſtration) to be peruſed by you at your leiſures, (I fear I have already too much intrenched upon your Patience in the peruſal of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Memorial.) And we will call it, <hi>The Parable of the Leaſees Leaguer, and a Deſcription of the</hi> Sub <hi>and Outward Pawn Tenants Camp:</hi> So that, Whereas I do perceive, that theſe Civil and Inteſtine Diviſions, Wars, Animoſities and Contentions among the conteſting Parties, the Domeſtick Inhabitants of your Pallace Royal, are ſtill like to continue many Summers Campagne; for the Drums do yet daily
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:171654:29"/>ſound in my ears, and <hi>ad arma, ad arma, inſonuit buccina,</hi> for new Voluntiers, whereby to re-inforce their Armies, unleſs you Right Honourable, and you Right Worſhipfull, who are the proper and onely Mediators in this Caſe, (by reaſon you can turn the ſcales at any time) do interpoſe by your Power, Grandeur and Authority, and to declare who have been and are ſtill the Aggreſſors: For it ſeems they have all referr'd themſelves, and will acquieſce in your Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, as appears by their ſeveral humble Petitions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in that behalf: So that <hi>London,</hi> this famous City of <hi>London,</hi> (being the moſt convenient and commodious) is the place aſſigned for the Congreſs of all the Plenipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiaries from their ſeveral Principals, upon that Account: And if wiſhes would avail, or turn any thing to Account, I could here make it my cordial Option, that this were the place alſo aſſigned for the Congreſs of the Deputies, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors and Plenipotentiaries of all thoſe conteſting Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which are at preſent at ſo great a variance among the Princes of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> and that his Majeſty of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> (Heavens proſper and preſerve him) were the ſole Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator and Umpire in all their Caſes, and becauſe I did perceive, that by reaſon of the remote diſtance that is at preſent between the Moderators and theſe Perſons before mentioned: And here for Illuſtrations ſake, we will now draw our Scene <hi>Colen,</hi> and all the Sub-Tenants, and Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Pawn-Tenants, encamped and intrenched about the ſaid City, Suburbs and parts adjacent thereof; and that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as they had already extremely ſuffered, and might do much more in their ſo honeſt and juſt Deſign, and for want of giving their Ambaſſadours, and by them their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derators, the true State and Information of their Caſe: And although at preſent they have a very numerous Army, and a large Train of Artillery, and a moſt Noble, Valiant, Courageous and well diſciplin'd Army, and have their Out-works, their deep Trenches, their Sconces, their Palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zadoes,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:171654:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>their Pioneers, their Counterſcarps, their Engineers, their Scouts abroad, their ſtrong Centinels upon their Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, their advantageous Poſts; and are alſo expert in the terms of Art when they are drawn up into <hi>Battalia,</hi> as their Wheelings, their Serings, their Facings, their Flankings, their Doublings, and their Front and Rear Diviſion, and their Center, in ſuch an excellent Order, and the like, whereby they do render themſelves worthy the Appellation of what they truly are, <hi>viz.</hi> The legitimate Sons of <hi>Mars:</hi> But yet notwithſtanding, for all this, they are in Quotidian Jeopardy, and in great danger of being beſieged and ſterved out by their Enemies, in their preſent Intrenchments; and ſhould they draw forth, and come to a pitch'd Battel, by reaſon of their moſt potent Aſſailants, which lie alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched round about them, that they have ſo many and ſuch powerfull Confederates, and having ſuch great ſtore of Ammunition, and in a Countrey where they have great ſtore of Forage for their Cavalry, and plenty of Proviſion for their Infantry, (in the which they are at preſent but at a very low ebbe) they dare not run the hazard of a total Engagement, (unleſs they were certain that their Guardian Angels, which are the worthy Members of the Grand Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, would appear and fight for them,) for fear they ſhould be totally routed, and ſhould be conſtrained to quit the Field, and to yield upon diſhonourable terms: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon during this preſent conjuncture, being unwilling to ſtand Neuter, (though peradventure I might have made ſome conſiderable advantage thereby) at length, upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious conſultation, I betook my ſelf unto the weakeſt (as having the beſt Cauſe, and ſo I hope I ſhall do the ſame, <hi>dum ſpiritus hos reget Artus,</hi>) and the moſt innocent ſide; And thereupon being oftentimes in their Leaguer, and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that their Enemies might be too hard for them as to matter of Intelligence, I did at laſt reſolve to imbarque my ſelf, (whereby to give you the beſt Information I could of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:171654:30"/>their preſent ſtate and condition) in the good Ship called the <hi>Happy Adventure</hi> and <hi>Bon Reſolution,</hi> and having weighed my Anchors, and hoiſed up my Sails, I committed my ſelf to the mercy of the Ocean, and although I met with many a bluſtring ſtorm, many croſs Winds, many dark nights (and here and there at Sea a Ship upon the wrack) yet having a good cauſe, a tight Veſſel, a Stout, Valiant, Sober, and well experienced Captain, a skilful Pilot, a rough hewen Boat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwain, a few ſtout and couragious Seamen, we did though through much difficulty and hard labour (and many times were conſtrained to pump hard for our own preſervation) work our Veſſel through them all.</p>
            <p>And although in our Voyage, we did many times Sail by the Ports and ſtronge Forts of our Enemies, and under their Caſtle-Walls, and within the reach of their Mortar pieces and their whole and demi Canons, yet ſtill when we did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend any real danger, clapping immediately up and bearing in our Top-Maſt head the antient Leaſees colours, (viz. Leaſees for 21 years) we paſſed them all along undiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. Neither did we make a <hi>Noverint univerſi,</hi> or put up any Bills before our departure whereby to procure any lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (for we tooke in none ſave only ballaſt, and ſome good proviſion for our intended Voyage) juſt as the Maſters of Ships do upon the Royal Exchange, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſuch a Ship now riding at Anchor in ſuch a Bay, within the River <hi>Rhine,</hi> and within ſuch a time is ready to depart, and bound (God willing) for the Port of <hi>London,</hi> the danger of the Seas only excepted, as having buſineſs of grand importance with the grand and Sub-Committee for <hi>Greſham</hi> affairs, ſitting at <hi>Mercers Chappel</hi> within the ſaid City, now this might have marred all, for then they would have ſent their privateers and iſſued out Letters of Mart againſt us, and had they taken us in our expedition, they had ſeized upon our Cargo and all our concerns, which would have been as bad as if we had been all blown up into the air by ſome unexpected accident of fire falling into our Powder room, but our Men being all
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:171654:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>obliged to ſecrecy. We came all clear along <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> making the Lands end, we took in a skilful Pilot from the <hi>Trinity-Houſe</hi> (for the better ſecurity of our veſſel through the Channel) till at length, by a brisk and proſperous gale, with all our Sails ſpread, our Standard at ſtern, and our Streamers abroad, we made our joyful and ſo long wiſhed for Port of <hi>London;</hi> and thus having brought our good Ship in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her deſired harbour, we will now caſt out our Anchors (only my <hi>Anchora ſpei</hi> I will ſtill keep within my own breaſt) and take ſome refreſhments and will now freely (with moſt humble ſervice) preſent the ſaid good Ship with all her Maſts Sails, Rigging, Guns, Mortar-Peices, Cables and Anchors, her whole Cargo, and all things whatſoever thereunto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining (unleſs your Noble and Generous minds will pleaſe to defray the charge of the ballaſt within her, and of ſome of the ordinary Seamen, that were employed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained upon this expedition) to your moſt Worthy Selves, and Remain (Right Honourable and Right Worſhipful)</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Obedient, moſt Obliged and moſt Faithful Servant to be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <head type="sub">Ad Candidum Lectorem.</head>
            <l>Authoris ſcripti ſi vis Cognoſcere Nomen,</l>
            <l>Quaerito in his literis, Lector amande ſcias.</l>
            <p>DEHNKRVY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:171654:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:171654:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
